<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A catechisme briefly opening the misterie of our redemption by Christ hauing the proues of euery point so annexed, and ioined vnder euery answer, that the ruder sort of people may be much furthered thereby, if they would vse a little diligence and endeuor to commit it to memory, or be much conuersant in reading thereof, or if they cannot read in hearing it read by others, vnto knowledge, and godlinesse.</title>
            <author>Settle, Thomas.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1587</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 124 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 48 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A11949</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 22267</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S114769</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99849992</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99849992</idno>
            <idno type="VID">15173</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A11949)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 15173)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1584:29)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A catechisme briefly opening the misterie of our redemption by Christ hauing the proues of euery point so annexed, and ioined vnder euery answer, that the ruder sort of people may be much furthered thereby, if they would vse a little diligence and endeuor to commit it to memory, or be much conuersant in reading thereof, or if they cannot read in hearing it read by others, vnto knowledge, and godlinesse.</title>
                  <author>Settle, Thomas.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[94] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by W. How, for Henry Car, and are to be sold at the Blasing Starre in Paules Churchyard,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1587]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>By Thomas Settle.</note>
                  <note>Publication date from STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-F (-F8, blank?).</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Catechisms, English --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:15173:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A CATECHISME <hi>briefly opening the miſterie of</hi> our redemption by Chriſt, hauing the <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>es of euery point ſo annexed, and ioined</hi> vnder euery anſwer, that the ruder ſort of <hi>people, may be much furthered thereby, if they</hi> vvould vſe a little diligence and endeuour to commit it to memory, or be much con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſant in reading thereof, or if they cannot read in hearing it read by others, vnto knovvledge, and godlineſſe.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Philipp.</hi> 1.9.10.</bibl> And this I pray, that your Loue may yet more and more abound in knovvledge and all Iudgement, that ye may knovv things vvhich differ, that ye may be ſyncere, and go forvvard in a blameleſſe courſe vntill the day of Chriſt.</q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Prouerb.</hi> 3.13.14.15.</bibl> Bleſſed is the man that findeth vviſdome, and the man that getteth vnderſtanding. For the merchandiſe therof is better then the merchandiſe of ſiluer, and the gaine therof is better then gold, it is more pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious then pearles, and all that thou canſt deſire are not to be compared vnto her.</q>
            <p>
               <hi>Seene and allowed by authoritie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Printed by W. How, for Henry Car, and <hi>are to be ſold at the Blaſing ſtarre in</hi> Paules Churchyard.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:15173:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:15173:2"/>
            <head>To the Right worſhipful <hi>maister Henry Warner</hi> Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quier, &amp; the vertuous Gentlewoman <hi>his wife, T.S. wiſheth grace, and mercie from</hi> God, thorough Chriſt Ieſus, and daily ſupplie of all godlineſſe, and vertue, the right directors to, and augmentors of all true worſhip.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Lord (Right worſhipfull) the moſt wiſe dispoſer of all actions, hauing giuen vnto me his leaſt able miniſter, an entrance into the Towne of <hi>Mildenhall,</hi> to publiſh there in the cares of that great people, according to his grace b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſtowed vpon me, his glorious Goſpell: I was ſtreightway, after I had ſome knowledge of their ſtate, moued with com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſsion towards them, and framed my ſelfe ſo neere as I could, to vſe ſuch a familiar, and plaine kind of teaching, as I thought to ſerue moſt for their vnderſtanding and capacitie. And although I had not granted vnto mee, (which was neuer yet granted to any faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full miniſter) to pleaſe, &amp; approue my doings to all: yet a fewe skorners ſet apart, which ſeem as the Prophet ſpeaketh,<note place="margin">E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> 
               <hi>To haue made
<pb facs="tcp:15173:3"/>a couenant with death, and to bee at an agreement with hell,</hi> being more deuout to ſerue <hi>Bacchus,</hi> then the true God: and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore can like of no Prophet, except ſuch, as ſaith an other Scripture, <hi>Can walke in a li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſpirit,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mich. 2.11.</note> 
               <hi>and propheſie vnto them of wine, and ſtrong drinke:</hi> And a few other which being altogether worldly minded, be froſen in their dregges; which ſeeme to haue made their large Fen their God; it pleaſed God to make the reſt, likers &amp; allowers of the holy doctrine, wiſhing to haue the ſame con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued amongſt them, and willing to impart ſomething of their ſubſtance vnto the diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer, towards his maintenance and liuing. In the behalfe of theſe, (Sir) I doo vnfainedly thanke &amp; bleſſe God the Father, Lord of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen and earth, by his Sonne Chriſt, conceiuing no ſmall hope, through his bleſsing, of their more increaſing and growing in faith and godlines, which God grant vnto them for his Chriſt his ſake Amen In the behalfe of thoſe, I do earneſtly pray, inforcing my ſelfe in all my doctrine,<note place="margin">Iude. 23.</note> as the Apoſtle <hi>Iude</hi> ſaith, to ſaue them with feare, and to pull them out of the fire, wiſhing that at any time God would giue them repentance, that they may come to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendment, out of the ſnare of the Diuell. But
<pb facs="tcp:15173:3"/>if they will not heare this, <hi>My ſoule ſhall weepe in ſecrete for their pride,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ierem. 13.17</note> (as the Prophet ſpeaketh) <hi>&amp; mine eie ſhall weepe &amp; drop downe teares to ſee Gods iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes vpon them.</hi> And now if I might ſpeake of your worſhip without ſuſpition of flatterie, &amp; coorying of fauour, by your dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent attending vpon the hearing, accompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned alwaies with your vertuous wife, moſt godlily likewiſe dispoſed to heare the holy word of God, and ſo much as might be your whole familie And by your good countena<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce moſt cheerefully ſhewed vnto me, a poore mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter of God, that I may not ſpeake of other your beneficence towardes mee, you moſt eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly declared, not only what loue your ſelfe had vnto the truth of God, that is his word, &amp; his pure and holy worſhip, but alſo your care by your godly exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple to draw others to like and allow of the ſame, that ſo Chriſt Ieſus might be enterteined &amp; his kingdome erected at <hi>Mildenhall.</hi> And I cannot forget how (which did declare your deſire and care to haue the word of Gods grace, that is the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel continued at <hi>Mildenhall,</hi> for the ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the people) you ſpake to the Right ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norable the Lord <hi>North,</hi> comming ouer to his houſe at <hi>Mildenhall,</hi> not only to ſhew me his
<pb facs="tcp:15173:4"/>fauourable countenance, for my continuance at <hi>Mildenhal,</hi> but alſo to procure me a more ample, and large ſalery and ſtipend: which thing his Honour, of his godly diſpoſition vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Religion, was willing to doo. In conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of theſe things, as they concerne Gods glorie, firſt I giue God hartie thanks: Second<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly as they concerne the helpe of me his Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, not otherwiſe knowing how to requite a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny way your Worſhips good will, as a teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monie of a gratefull minde, I beſtowe vpon your Worſhip, &amp; the vertuous Gentlewoman your wife, a litle <hi>Catechiſme,</hi> which I haue lately made, in my ſmall iudgement, not alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether vnfit (for indeed I laboured to make it fit) for the ſtate of the inhabitants of <hi>Mil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denhall,</hi> not for any great vſe of your ſelues (for I verily perſwade my ſelfe, that you haue not now neede to learne the firſt prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples of the word of God, but are able to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſt much ſtronger meat,) but for the vſe of your babes, your two ſonnes, and daughter, and others which afterwards it may pleaſe God to giue, and bleſſe you withall, whome I doo not doubt, to be inſtructed in the princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of Religion, ſo ſoone as they haue laid away their ſtammering tongues, according to Gods commaundement giuen to all parents,<note place="margin">Deut. 6.7.</note>
               <pb facs="tcp:15173:4"/>without exception of degree,<note place="margin">Pſal. 78. ℣ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 5, 6, 7. Epheſ. 6.4.</note> and condition in the world it will be vnto you both, no lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle care and ſtudie: which that it may be ſo, I ſhall daily pray. Accept (good Sir) of this mine enterpriſe, as I truſt you will; And thus I take my leaue, beſeeching God that yee doo none euill, that his good graces may be multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied vpon you, and that your whole ſpirit, ſoule, and bodie, may be kept blameleſſe vnto the comming of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your worſhips in all godly</hi> dutifulnes moſt readie <hi>Thomas Settle.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:15173:5"/>
            <head>
               <hi>To the Chriſtian Reader, and</hi> eſpeciallie to the inhabitantes of <hi>Mil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denhall</hi> in the Countie of <hi>Suffolke,</hi> for <hi>whoſe cauſe chiefly this little</hi> Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>techiſme was written, grace, mercie, and peace.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Fter ſo many Catechiſmes of ſo many good and god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly men had beene already publiſhed in our Church, if thou demaundeſt why nowe I doe aduenture the publiſhing of this of mine, as though I would ſeem to accuſe them of ſome neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence, or want in that behalfe, or to ad vnto them: I aunſwere, that my mind was free from any ſuch purpoſe. But as they, in ſtudie and care I do not doubt, to fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther religion and godlineſſe, did take li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertie vnto themſelues, in forme as they be extant, to frame and ſet foorth theirs, ſo haue I done. They haue written ſome largely, ſome briefly, and ſome haue kept a meane betweene long and ſhort, and I haue laboured, if not to bee the briefeſt, yet to come as neere it as I might. They ſome haue quoted for confirmation in their margent, ſome haue omitted quota<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,
<pb facs="tcp:15173:5"/>and ſome haue prooues ſet forth at large by directions alphabeticall; as eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one of them thought beſt, ſo haue they proceeded. I haue made proofe of euerie anſwere immediately vpon the anſwere, and almoſt made the wordes of the text the anſwere, hoping thereby the more to allure the reader and hearer. God make me partaker of my hope, and my godlie brethren of theirs. And thou (good Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der) remember, in the bowels of Chriſt I beſeech thee, that the more paines I &amp; my brethren beſtow for thine inſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on by preaching &amp; writing, the more and greeuous ſhal be thy condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation if thou profit not by it, which thing would be our griefe. Conſider what I ſay, &amp; the Lord giue thee vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Thine in Chriſt,</hi> Th. Settle.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="catechism">
            <pb facs="tcp:15173:6"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:15173:6"/>
            <head>¶ <hi>A CATECHISME,</hi> briefly vnfoulding the myſterie of <hi>our redemption by Chriſt, with</hi> other neceſsary points of Diuini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie thereunto annexed.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>HO made you, and to what end were you made?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>God, &amp; for his glory (as ſaith the Prophet <hi>Eſay</hi>) chapiter 43. <hi>I created him for my glorie,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eſay. 43. ℣ſe 7.21.</note> 
               <hi>formed him and made him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſt. <hi>What is God?</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> Euen as (proclaiming his owne name in <hi>Exodus 34.</hi>) be deſcribeth him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe,<note place="margin">Exod. 34. ℣ſ. 5.6.</note> ſaying: <hi>The Lord, the Lord, ſtrong mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifull, and gratious, ſlowe to anger, and abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant in goodnes and truth, reſeruing mercie for thouſands, forgiuing iniquitie, tranſgreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, and ſinne and not making the wicked in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent.</hi> In the fourth of the goſpell after <hi>Iohn<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> he is ſaid to be a ſpirit.<note place="margin">Iohn. 4.24. Exod. 6.3. Iehoua what it doth ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifie.</note> In <hi>Exodus</hi> the ſixt, he calleth his owne name <hi>Ieho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uah,</hi> which is as much to ſay, as one that hath his béeing of himſelfe: which name importeth his euerlaſtingnes.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:15173:7"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu. <hi>What can you ſay further concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning God?</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> Verily that he is thrée diſtinct per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, that is, Father, Sonne, and holie ghoſt, and yet in ſubſtance one God one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie. As <hi>Iohn</hi> the Apoſtle euidently tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth in the fift chap. of his firſt Epiſtle, ſaying:<note place="margin">1. Iohn. 5. v. 7.</note> 
               <hi>For there are three which beare re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord in heauen, the Father, the worde, and the holy Ghoſt: and theſe three are one.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu. <hi>How doe you proue that the holy Ghoſt is God?</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> In <hi>28.</hi> of <hi>Mathew,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Math. 8.19.</note> Chriſt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth to baptize in the name of the holie Ghoſt. Now this is certaine, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> baptiſme is to be miniſtred in no name,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 1. verſ. 14.15.</note> but in the name of God. But it béeing co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>manded to bee miniſtred in the name of the holy ghoſt, doth manifeſtly proue that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holy Ghoſt is God. In the <hi>5.</hi> of the <hi>Actes, Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> ſaith vnto <hi>Ananias:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Act. 5. verſ. 3.4.5.</note> 
               <hi>Why hath Sathan filled thine hart that thou ſhouldeſt lye to the Holy Ghoſt? &amp;c. How is it thou haſt conceiued this thing in thine hart? Thou haſt not lyed vnto men, but vnto God.</hi> This place alſo proueth in plaine words that the Holie ghoſt is God.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu. <hi>You ſaid euen now that God made
<pb facs="tcp:15173:7"/>you, and you ſhewed to what end: ſhew now in what ſtate he made you?</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> According to his owne image, that is to ſay, in righteouſnes and true holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, as <hi>Paule</hi> expoundeth it in the <hi>4.</hi> to the <hi>Epheſians,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Epheſ. 4.24.</note> calling it béeing repaired in Gods electe by the ſpirite, in other words the new man.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu. <hi>Doe you continue in that ſtate of righteouſnes and true holineſſe wherein you were at the firſt by God created?</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> No verily: For <hi>Paule</hi> witneſſeth in the <hi>3.</hi> to the <hi>Romaines,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 3.25.</note> that all haue ſinned and are depriued of the glorie of God. And in the ſecond to the <hi>Epheſians</hi> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame Apoſtle ſaith,<note place="margin">Epheſ. 2, 3.</note> y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they as wel as o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers were by nature y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of wrath. And as <hi>Dauid</hi> in the <hi>51.</hi> pſalme confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth, ſo may all others,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſal. 51, 5.</note> that they were conceiued and borne in ſinne.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu. <hi>You ſaid euen nowe that you were made after the Image of God righteous and holy, and nowe yee confeſſe that ye were borne a ſinner: how can this be?</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ. Adam</hi> the firſt man was created after the Image of God righteous &amp; ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie, and ſo I, and al other in him our firſt parent, were created righteous and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie:
<pb facs="tcp:15173:8"/>But when he by his ſinne, in eating the forbidden fruite, made himſelfe vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteous and vnholy, then I, and all the world béeing then in his loines, (for <hi>who</hi> ſaith <hi>Iob</hi> in the <hi>14.</hi> chapiter of his booke, <hi>can bring a cleane thing out of filthineſse</hi>) were made vnrighteous and vnholy.<note place="margin">Iob. 14.4.</note> And to proue that man was made righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous at the beginning, the <hi>Preacher</hi> ſaith in the <hi>7.</hi> of his booke: <hi>Onely loe, this haue I found,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſ. 7.27.</note> 
               <hi>that God hath made man righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous; But they haue ſought many inuentions:</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu. <hi>Do you then affirme that the ſinne which</hi> Adam <hi>committed is alſo your ſin?</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> Yea verily: for ſo affirmeth holie Scripture in the <hi>5.</hi> to the <hi>Romaines: <hi>By one mans diſobedience many</hi>
               </hi> (that is all) <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came ſinners.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 5.19.</note> And againe in the ſame cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piter. <hi>By the offence of one the fault came on all men.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 5.18.</note> Yea, &amp; a little before in the ſame chapter the apoſtle ſaith; that <hi>Death raig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned from <hi>Adam</hi> to <hi>Moſes,</hi> euen ouer them alſo that ſinned not,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 5.14.</note> 
               <hi>after the like manner of the tranſgreſsion of <hi>Adam:</hi>
               </hi> he meaneth e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen the very babes and young ſucking children, to bee by <hi>Adams</hi> ſinne ſubiecte vnto death and damnation.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu. <hi>Doe you thinke, that if your ſinne
<pb facs="tcp:15173:8"/>in</hi> Adam <hi>in eating the forbidden fruite, were not laid vnto your charge, that you ſhould bee righteous and holie, and free from ſinne?</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> No verily: for the ſcripture crieth out euerie where to the contrarie. Our nature was ſo poiſoned thorow <hi>Adams</hi> ſinne, that we can do nothing but ſinne. As it is written in <hi>Geneſis</hi> the ſixt: <hi>The Lorde ſawe that the wickedneſse of man was great in the earth,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Geneſ. 6.5.</note> 
               <hi>and all the imaginations of the thoughts of his heart were onely euill continually.</hi> And <hi>Paule</hi> confeſſeth ſaying in the <hi>7.</hi> to the <hi>Romaines:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 7.12.</note> 
               <hi>I knowe that in mee</hi> (that is in my fleſh) <hi>dwelleth no good thing; for to will is preſent with mee, but I find no meanes to performe that is good.</hi> And againe in the <hi>8.</hi> to the <hi>Romaines,</hi> it is ſaide,<note place="margin">Rom. 8.3.</note> that <hi>The Lawe is weake thorowe the fleſh,</hi> that is to ſay, that the fleſh by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the corruption thereof,<note place="margin">No free will in man ſince Adams fal, or abilitie to do good.</note> and weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, is not of abilitie to performe the Lawe, which Law was ingrauen in <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dams</hi> hart. Finally, we may all that are deſcended of <hi>Adams</hi> race, cry out as it is in the <hi>130.</hi> pſalme:<note place="margin">Pſal. 130.3.</note> 
               <hi>If thou (O Lorde) ſtrait<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye markeſt iniquities, O Lorde, who ſhall ſtand?</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:15173:9"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu. <hi>What then is the ſtate and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of you, and all other, through your ſinne in Adam, and your owne daily ſins, by reaſon of your corruption of nature drawne from Adam?</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> Moſt woofull truly &amp; miſerable is mine, and the ſtate of all men elſe in themſelues becauſe of ſin: for it is writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten in the <hi>5.</hi> to the <hi>Romaines:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 5.18.</note> 
               <hi>By the of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of one the fault came on all men to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</hi> And againe in the <hi>2.</hi> to the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maines: Tribulation &amp; anguiſh ſhalbe vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the ſoule of euery man that doth euill.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 2.9.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu. <hi>Set forth yet more fully the pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment of ſinne, and the ſtate of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation.</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu.</hi> In the <hi>30.</hi> chapter of <hi>Eſai</hi> it is ſaid, <hi>Tophet</hi> (which by a borowed ſpeach is <hi>Hell</hi>) <hi>is prepared of old,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eſai. 30.33.</note> 
               <hi>it is euen prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red for the king, he hath made it deepe and large, the burning thereof is fire and much wood, the breath of the Lord like a riuer of brimſtone dooth kindle it.</hi> In the <hi>66.</hi> of the ſame Prophet,<note place="margin">Eſai. 66.24.</note> it is alſo ſaid: <hi>And they</hi> (that is the godly) <hi>ſhall go forth, and looke vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the carcaſſes of the men that haue tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſed againſt me, for their worme ſhall not die, neyther ſhall their fire be quenched, and
<pb facs="tcp:15173:9"/>they shal be an abhorring to all flesh.</hi> In the <hi>8.</hi> of <hi>Mathew</hi> it is ſaide,<note place="margin">Math, 8, 12.</note> 
               <hi>The children of the kingdome</hi> (that is the <hi>Iewes</hi>) <hi>shalbe caſt out into vtter darkeneſse, where shalbe wee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping and gnashing of teeth.</hi> In the <hi>21.</hi> of the <hi>Reuelation</hi> it is written, that <hi>The fearefull, vnbeleeuing,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Reuel, 21, 8.</note> 
               <hi>and abhominable shal haue their portion in the lake which bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth with fire and brimſtone, which is the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond death.</hi> In conſideration of which ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treme puniſhment, the wicked at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ming of Chriſt ſhal ſay, as it is in the <hi>6.</hi> of the <hi>Reuelation,</hi> to the mountains &amp; to the rockes, <hi>Fall vpon vs,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Reuel, 6, ℣ſe 16, 17.</note> 
               <hi>&amp; hide vs from the preſence of him that ſitteth on the throne, and from the wrath of the Lambe, for the great day of his wrath is come, and who canne ſtand?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu. <hi>O moſt wofull depth of miſerie, and cruell calamitie becauſe of ſinne, but is there no meane to auoyde this woe?</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> One onely meanes to eſcape is prouided by God.<note place="margin">Acts, 4, 12.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu. <hi>Shew what it is?</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> God ſtraightway after <hi>Adams</hi> fall, raiſed him and all other his elect vp againe vnto hope by the promiſe of a ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour
<pb facs="tcp:15173:10"/>to vanquiſh the power of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than, &amp; to ſet the enthralled frée: as ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareth in <hi>Geneſis 3.</hi> where it is denou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced againſt Sathan,<note place="margin">Gen, 3, 15.</note> that <hi>The ſeede of the woman ſhould bruſe his head.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu. <hi>Did any deſerte of</hi> Adam <hi>mooue God hereunto?</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> None at all. It was onely Gods loue, pitie, and compaſſion that procured this ſaluation: As it is written in the <hi>3</hi> of <hi>Iohns</hi> goſpel;<note place="margin">Iohn 3, 16.</note> 
               <hi>God ſo loued the world, that he gaue his onely begotten ſonne, that euery one that beleeueth in him might not perishe but haue eternall life.</hi> And againe in <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans 5.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom, 5. ver, 8</note> 
               <hi>But God ſetteth out his loue towards vs, ſeeing that while we were yet ſinners</hi> (yea and a little after <hi>Enemies</hi>) <hi>Chriſt dyed for vs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu. <hi>What natures were in Chriſt?</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> Two. The nature of man, and the nature of God in one perſon: As it is proued by theſe words in <hi>Romanes 9.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 9, 4. 1, Iohn, 5, 20.</note> 
               <hi>Of whome</hi> (that is of the Iſralites) <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the fleſh Chriſt came, who is God ouer all, bleſsed for euer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu. <hi>Why was it needfull that our Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemer ſhould be man?</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> That God might ſatiſfie his Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice
<pb facs="tcp:15173:10"/>in puniſhing man (as he threatned if his commandement ſhould be broken when he gaue it firſt to <hi>Adam</hi>) for that which man had offended. Which thing the Apoſtle ſéemeth to ſay in <hi>Hebrews 2.</hi> where he ſaith:<note place="margin">Heb, 2, verſe 14, 15, 16, 17</note> 
               <hi>Foraſmuch as the children were partakers of fleſh and bloud, he alſo him ſelfe tooke part with them, that he might de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy through death him that had the power of death (that is the diuell) and that he might deliuer all them which for feare of death were all their l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>fe time ſubiect vnto bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage.</hi> And <hi>Peter</hi> ſayth in the third cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piter of his firſt Epiſtle:<note place="margin">1. Pet. 3, 18.</note> 
               <hi>Chriſt hath once ſuffered for ſinnes, the iuſt for the vniuſt to bring vs to good,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu. <hi>Why was it neceſſary that our re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemer ſhould be God?</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> To the intent that the infirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of his manhood might be ſuſtained by his Godhead, that ſo he might ouercome death, &amp; the ſorrows of death. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it is ſaide in <hi>Romans <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</hi> that <hi>He was declared mightily to be the ſonne of God,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom, 1, 4.</note> 
               <hi>tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching the ſpirit of ſanctification, by his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection from the dead.</hi> And againe the ſame Apoſtle ſaith in <hi>2.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1, Cor, 13, 4.</note> 
               <hi>Corinthians</hi> cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piter <hi>13. <hi>For although hee was crucified ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording
<pb facs="tcp:15173:11"/>to his infirmitie</hi>
               </hi> (that is his Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hoode) <hi>yet doth he lyue by the power of God.</hi> If hee had béene but onely man, he could not haue ouercome death, and therefore <hi>Peter</hi> in the third chapiter of his firſt e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtle, aſcribeth the quickning of Chriſt (that is the raiſing of his body fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> death) to the ſpirit,<note place="margin">1. Pet. 3.18.</note> that is to the diuine power.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. Was Chriſt himſelfe who was borne of a ſinfull woman, free from the contagion and infection of ſinne? You al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leadged out of <hi>Iob</hi> the 14. chapiter, <hi>That none could bryng that is pure out of filthy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſse.</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> If Chriſt had not béene frée from the infection of ſin, be had béene vnméete to haue ranſomed and deliuered other there from; And therefore it is ſaide in the <hi>7.</hi> to the <hi>Hebrewes,</hi> that <hi>Such an high Prieſt it becomes vs to haue,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heb. 7.26.</note> 
               <hi>as is holy, harm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe, vndefiled, ſeperate from ſinners, &amp; made higher then the heauens.</hi> And in the fift of the <hi>2.</hi> to the <hi>Corinthians Paule</hi> ſaith; <hi>He was made ſinne for vs which knew no ſinne.</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Cor, 5, 21.</note> And therefore to the intent he might bée frée from ſinne, he was conceiued in the wombe of the virgine,<note place="margin">Luke, 1, 35.</note> as appeareth in the firſt of <hi>Luke,</hi> by the holy ghoſt.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:15173:11"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. Doe you thinke that the bodilye death which Chriſt did ſuffer, was ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient to deliuer all mankinde from the puniſhment due both to their bodies and ſoules?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Notwithſtanding that the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture oftentimes aſcribeth for giuenes of ſinnes, &amp; our redemption to the ſhedding of his bloud, as in the firſt to the <hi>Epheſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans; <hi>By whom we haue redemption through his bloud, euen the forgiuenes of ſins.</hi>
               </hi>
               <note place="margin">Epheſ. 1.7.</note> And in the firſt chap. of the firſt epiſtle of <hi>Peter: <hi>Knowing that you were not redeemed with corruptible things, as ſiluer and gold,</hi>
               </hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Pet. 1. ℣ſe 18, 19.</note> 
               <hi>fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> your vaine conuerſation, receiued by the traditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the Fathers: but with the pretious bloud of Chriſt, as of a lambe vndefiled, and without ſpot,</hi> and many ſuche like places. Yet we are alwaies to vnderſtand, that a ſpeciall part of our redemption conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteth in the ſufferings of his ſoule. For therin he bickered, &amp; had combat with al the powers of hell &amp; damnation, which was due for our ſins, the ſtings, horrors &amp; ſorrows (as <hi>Peter Acts 2.</hi> calleth them) whereof, cauſed him to ſweat drops like water &amp; bloud, trickling downe from his body: ſo great was his agony,<note place="margin">Luke 22, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> as <hi>Luke</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:15173:12"/>in the <hi>22.</hi> chapter recordeth, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels came to comfort him. Againe, vpon the croſſe the wrath of God did ſo preſſe his ſoule for our ſinnes, that for extreme anguiſh this pitifull exclamation was wreſted from his mouth;<note place="margin">Mat, 27, 49.</note> 
               <hi>My God, my God, why haſt thou forſaken me?</hi> Who can think that theſe ſtrong cryings &amp; teares, as in <hi>Hebrews 5.</hi> they are tearmed,<note place="margin">Heb, 5, 7.</note> were euer in the Son of God, for &amp; becauſe of a bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily death, which we do ſée many weake men (yea, which ſuffer for no good cauſe amongſt vs) moſt conſtantly to endure. In theſe his ſufferinges he hath ſpoyled death &amp; hell, as it is written in threate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning wiſe; <hi>O Death, I will be thy death, O graue,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hoſea 13, 14</note> 
               <hi>I will be thy deſtruction.</hi> And againe in <hi>Colloſsians 2.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Colloſ. 2, 15.</note> 
               <hi>And hee hath ſpoyled the principalities and powers, and hath made a ſhew of them openly, and tryumphed ouer them in the ſame croſse.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu. <hi>But nowe ſith none can enioy the ioies of heauen and eternal life, but thoſe that fulfill the will of God, and perfecte obedience vnto his Lawe. Howe ſhall wee poore ſinners doe in this be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>halfe?</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> The goodnes of our God hath in
<pb facs="tcp:15173:12"/>this behalfe alſo prouided for vs, raiſing vp for vs a mightie ſaluation. The Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle ſaith in the <hi>4.</hi> to the <hi>Galathians,</hi> that <hi>Chriſt was made vnder the law, that he might redeeme them which were vnder the lawe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gal, 4, v. 4<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 5.</note> 
               <hi>that they might receiue the adoption of ſons.</hi> And againe he ſaith in the ſecond to the <hi>Colloſsians, <hi>And you which were deade in ſinnes,</hi>
               </hi>
               <note place="margin">Colloſ. 2. ver. 13, 14, 15.</note> 
               <hi>and in the vncircumciſion of your flesh hath he quickned together with him,</hi> (that is Chriſt) <hi>forgiuing all your treſpaſses, and putting out the hande writing of ordinances that was againſt vs, which was contrarie to vs, he euen tooke it out of the way, and faſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned it vnto his croſse.</hi> Againe,<note place="margin">1 Rom, 10, 4</note> in <hi>Romans</hi> the <hi>10. <hi>Chriſt is the end of the law for righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſnes vnto euerie one that beleeueth.</hi>
               </hi>
               <note place="margin">1, Cor, 1, 30.</note> Laſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in <hi>1. Corinthians 1.</hi> it is ſaid, that <hi>Chriſt is made of God our wiſedome, righteouſneſſe, ſanctification, &amp; redemption</hi> (that is to ſay) that whatſoeuer we haue néede of to the obteining of eternal life &amp; ſaluation, we haue it in him as in a full fraught and plentifull ſtorehouſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu. <hi>Doth this ſaluatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> pertaine to all, and ſhall all be partakers of the ſame?</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> The ſaluation is offered to all, but none ſhal haue it but thoſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> beléeue.
<pb facs="tcp:15173:13"/>As it is written in the <hi>16.</hi> of the goſpell after <hi>Marke:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mark. 16<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 15</note> 
               <hi>Go ye into all the world, and preach the goſpell to euery creature; He that shall beleeue and be baptized shall be ſaued, and he that wil not beleeue shalbe damned.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu. What is it to beleeue?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> To beléeue, is to bee fully per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded that God the father, which hath made me the promiſe of ſaluation in his Sonne, wil faithfully performe his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe vnto me. For as <hi>Abraham</hi> hauing Gods promiſe made vnto him, as the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle affirmeth in the <hi>4.</hi> to the <hi>Romans</hi> did not doubt of the promiſe through vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beliefe,<note place="margin">Rom. 4. ℣ſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>0.21.</note> but was ſtrengthened in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> faith, and gaue glory to God, béeing fully aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, that he which had promiſed was al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo able to do it: euen ſo alſo wee hauing Gods promiſe: (for ſaith the apoſtle in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame place, it is not written for him on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie,<note place="margin">Rom. 4.23.</note> but alſo for vs) muſt not doubt of the promiſe through vnbeliefe, but bee fully aſſured to obteine it, God béeing both a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and faithfull.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. <hi>How is faith wrought in men?</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> Thrée thinges eſpecially for the woorking of faith are to bee noted from the Scripture. Firſt the preaching of
<pb facs="tcp:15173:13"/>Gods word: For ſaith the Apoſtle <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans</hi> the <hi>10. <hi>How ſhall they heare without a preacher,</hi>
               </hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 10, 15.</note> 
               <hi>and how shall they preach except they be ſent, &amp;c.</hi> Then faith is by hearing and hearing by the word of God.<note place="margin">1. Cor. 1.21.</note> And a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine in the <hi>1. Corinthians. 1. <hi>It pleaſed God by the foolishneſſe of preaching to ſaue them that beleeue.</hi>
               </hi>
               <note place="margin">Iohn. 11.20.</note> Alſo <hi>Iohn</hi> the <hi>11. <hi>I pray not</hi>
               </hi> (ſaith Chriſt) <hi>for theſe (my diſciples) alone, but for them alſo which shall beleeue in me through their word, that is their prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu. <hi>What is the ſecond thing that you note from the ſcriptures to be neceſſary to the begetting of faith?</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> The ſecond is, that hée whiche preacheth be ſent &amp; authoriſed of God. For <hi>how</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle in the <hi>10.</hi> to the <hi>Romans</hi>) <hi>shall they preach except they be ſent?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 10.15.</note> Againe the Prophet <hi>Ieremie</hi> in his <hi>23.</hi> chapter ſaith:<note place="margin">Iere. 23, 32.</note> 
               <hi>I ſent them not nor commanded them, therfore they being no pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit to this people.</hi> Our ſauiour Chriſt ſaith in the <hi>10.</hi> of <hi>Iohn:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iohn. 10. ℣ſ. 1, 2.</note> That <hi>he that entreth not in by the doore into the sheepefold, but climeth vp ſome otherway he is a theefe and a robber.</hi> And in the <hi>10. verſe</hi> he ſaith, That <hi>a theefe commeth not but for to ſteale,
<pb facs="tcp:15173:14"/>to kill and to deſtroy,</hi> ſo farre is it of that they ſhall beget men to the faith. <hi>Iob</hi> calleth ſuch a meſſenger a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand in his <hi>33.</hi> chapter.<note place="margin">Iob. 33, 23.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu <hi>What is the third thing?</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> The working of the Holy ghoſt in the miniſtration of the word with power in the hearers harts, as by theſe places of Scripture is, and by many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther may be proued. <hi>Paule</hi> in the fourth chapter of his former Epiſtle to the <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinthians</hi> threatning to come to <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinth,</hi> to make triall of the doctrine of the falſe Apoſtles, which were ſo high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly extolled, and of the effectualneſſe thereof affirmeth,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 4. ℣ſ. 19, 20.</note> that <hi>the kingdome of God</hi> (that is the miniſtrie of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell) <hi>ſtands not in word but in the power of the Spirite.</hi> In the ſecond chapter of the ſame Epiſtle he ſaith:<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Cor. 2, 4.</note> 
               <hi>Neither ſtood my word and my preaching in the intiſing ſpeach of mans wiſedome, but in plaine eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of the ſpirite and power, that your faith might not bee in the wiſedome of men but in the power of God.</hi> Againe in the former Epiſtle to the <hi>Theſſalonians</hi> the firſt chapter:<note place="margin">1. Theſſ. 1, 5.</note> 
               <hi>For our goſpell was not vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you in word onely, but alſo in power
<pb facs="tcp:15173:14"/>and in the Holy ghoſt.</hi> In all theſe thrée places <hi>Paule</hi> ſetteth foorth the power of the Holy ghoſt in begetting of faith by the outward miniſtrie of his preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. In the fift chapter to the <hi>Galathi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans Paule</hi> ſaith:<note place="margin">Galat. 5.22.</note> 
               <hi>The fruit of the ſpirite is loue, ioy, peace, long ſuffering, gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleneſſe, goodneſſe, faith, meekeneſſe, tempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rancie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu. <hi>What men are meet for the plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of faith?</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> Thoſe onely that haue a féeling of their owne miſerie and woe, due from Gods inſtice for their ſinnes. For thoſe onely dooth Chriſt call in the eleuenth of <hi>Mathew,</hi> ſaying:<note place="margin">Math. 11, 28</note> 
               <hi>Come vnto me all yee that are weary and laden and I will eaſe you.</hi> In the ſecond of the <hi>Acts</hi> we read that thoſe that were pricked in their harts, and ſaid vnto <hi>Peter</hi> and the other Apoſtles,<note place="margin">Acts. 2. ℣ſe 37, 38, 39.</note> 
               <hi>Men and brethren what ſhall we do,</hi> immediatly after beléeued.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu. <hi>To what head or point of reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion do you refer this ſorrow and trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling conceiued of the ſight of Gods diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſure for ſinne.</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> To the point of Repentance,<note place="margin">Acts. 2 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>7.</note> as a foregoer thereof in the elect.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:15173:15"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu. <hi>What is Repentance?</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> Repentance is a turning fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſin vnto God,<note place="margin">What Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance is.</note> that is to ſay, a framing of our whole life to obey him. And y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> word that the Scripture vſeth moſt common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to expreſſe it by, doth ſignifie a change or alteration of the minde. That new birth which our ſauiour Chriſt ſpeaketh of in the <hi>3.</hi> of <hi>Iohn</hi> vnto <hi>Nicodemus</hi> is nothing but Repe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tance.<note place="margin">Iohn. 3, 3.</note> It is called Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generation. Regeneration or Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance hath two parts repreſented in ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptiſme, that is, Dying vnto ſinne, called mortification, termed in the Scripture circumciſion of the hart: And newneſſe at life. Both theſe partes of repentance are in ſundrie places of the Scriptures expreſſed. As in the <hi>2.</hi> chapter vnto <hi>Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus</hi> in theſe words:<note place="margin">Titus. 2. ℣ſe 11, 12.</note> 
               <hi>For that grace of God that bringeth ſaluation vnto all men hath appeared, and teacheth vs, to deny vngodli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, and worldly luſts,</hi> (this is Mortificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on) <hi>and to liue ſobe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ly, righteouſly, and god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in this preſent world</hi> (this is Newneſſe of life.) In the <hi>2.</hi> to the <hi>Colloſsians</hi> theſe two parts are alſo expreſſed, where the Apoſtle ſaith:<note place="margin">Coloſſ. 2. ℣ſ. 11, 12.</note> 
               <hi>In whom alſo ye are circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſed with circumciſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> made without hands,
<pb facs="tcp:15173:15"/>by putting off the ſinfull body of the flesh through the circumciſion of Chriſt, in that ye are buried with him thorough baptiſme,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Epheſ. 4. ℣ſe 22, 23.24.</note> 
               <hi>in whom ye are alſo raiſed vp together through the faith of the operation of God.</hi> In the <hi>6.</hi> of the epiſtle to the <hi>Romans,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 6.4.</note> and in the <hi>4.</hi> of the firſt epiſtle of <hi>Peter,</hi> both theſe parts are manifeſtly expreſſed:<note place="margin">1. Pet. 4. ℣ſe 1, 2.</note> the one procéedeth of the force of Chriſts death, the other of his<note place="margin">n="*" Phil. 3, 10.</note> reſurrection.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu. <hi>How is repentance wrought in mans hart?</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> By the holy ghoſt in preaching of the lawes and the goſpell.<note place="margin">John 3, 5.</note> 
               <hi>Except a man</hi> (ſaith Chriſt) <hi>be borne of water and the Holy ghoſt, he ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not enter into the kingdome of God.</hi> Againe <hi>Paule</hi> ſaith in the <hi>6.</hi> of his firſt epiſtle to the <hi>Corinthians:</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Cor. 6.11.</note> 
               <hi>And ſuch were ſome of you, but ye are washed, but ye are ſanctified, but ye are iuſtified in the name of the Lord Ieſus, &amp; by the ſpirit of our God.</hi> And againe in the <hi>3.</hi> chapter of the ſeco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d epiſtle to the <hi>Corinthians:</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Cor. 1, 12.</note> 
               <hi>But we all be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold as in a mirrour the glory of the Lord with open face, and are chaunged into the ſame image from glory to glory as by the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu. <hi>You haue proued that Repentance
<pb facs="tcp:15173:16"/>is the worke of the Holy ghoſt. Now proue that it is in the miniſtry of the law and the goſpell.</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> In the <hi>1.</hi> chapter of <hi>Titus</hi> it is commaunded <hi>Titus</hi> that he ſhould ſharp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly rebuke the <hi>Cretians,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Titus. 1. ℣ſe 12, 13.</note> becauſe one of their own prophets witneſſeth that they were alwaies liers, euill beaſts, ſlow bellies, that they may bée ſound in the ſaith.<note place="margin">Rom. 3.20.</note> 
               <hi>The whole Scripture</hi> (both the law &amp; the goſpell) ſaith the ſame Apoſtle in the <hi>3.</hi> of his <hi>2.</hi> Epiſtle to <hi>Timothie,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Timoth. 3. ℣ſe 16, 17.</note> 
               <hi>is giuen by inſpiration from God, and is profitable to conuince, to correct, and to inſtruct, &amp;c.</hi> thus much for the miniſtry of the lawe. For the goſpell: Our Sauiour Chriſt ſaith in the fiftenth of <hi>Iohn: <hi>Nowe are yee cleane through the word that I haue ſpoken vnto you.</hi>
               </hi>
               <note place="margin">Iohn. 15, 3.</note> Alſo <hi>Peter</hi> ſaith in the <hi>1.</hi> chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of his firſt epiſtle: <hi>Being borne againe, not of mortall ſeede but of immortall,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Pet. 1.23.</note> 
               <hi>by the word of God.</hi> Laſtly in the twenty and ſix of the <hi>Acts,</hi> it is witneſſed, that <hi>Paule</hi> was ſent by Ieſus Chriſt by preaching the goſpell vnto the Gentiles, <hi>To open their eies,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Acts. 26, 18.</note> 
               <hi>that they might turne from dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes to light, and from the power of Satan to God, that they might receiue forgiuenes of
<pb facs="tcp:15173:16"/>ſinnes, &amp; inheritance among them that were Sanctified by faith in him.</hi> Thus it is plaine that Repentance is the worke of the Holy ghoſt, by the miniſtry of the law and the goſpell.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu. <hi>Whether is faith before Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, or Repentance before faith?</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> The queſtion is buſie: there is no doubt but faith &amp; repentance are very nigh adioined, as touching their begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, as is the cauſe and the effect. Let it ſuffice vs to know, that when a ſinner thorow the preaching of the lawe is throwne downe to the ſight of his deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued damnation, by the auenging iuſtice of God, that the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> (if he be Gods elect) faith in Gods promiſe of ſaluation in Chriſt is wrought in him by the preaching of the goſpell: whervpon followeth an ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred of ſinne and care to auoid it, a loue of righteouſnes and care to doo it, which are eſpeciall effects of repentance in to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of thankefulneſſe for ſaluation by Chriſt. The Scripture in ſundry places doth aſcribe ſanctification and purging of the hart vnto faith. As in the twentie and ſix of the <hi>Acts:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Acts. 26, 18<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </note> 
               <hi>That they may receiue forgiuenes of ſinnes, and inheritance among
<pb facs="tcp:15173:17"/>them which are ſanctified by faith in mee.</hi> Againe in the <hi>15. <hi>He put no difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene vs and them after that by faith he had purified their harts</hi>
               </hi> Now Sanctifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, regeneration, &amp; repentance being all one, it followeth that they are effects of faith. Further becauſe without faith (as the Apoſtle ſaith in the <hi>11.</hi> to the <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brewes</hi>) <hi>it is impoſsible to pleaſe God:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hebr. 11, 6.</note> &amp; in another place,<note place="margin">Rom. 14.23</note> 
               <hi>What ſoeuer is not of faith is ſinne.</hi> We haue moſt warrant to think that faith is before repentance. Not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding ſome writers are of mind that ſome part of repentance goeth be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore faith, and ſome part followeth as an effect therof.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu. <hi>When ceaſeth repentance in men?</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> When men ceaſe altogether to ſin: But ſin doth not ceaſe to be in the moſt holy man ſo long as he liueth, ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore men muſt continue repentance ſo long as they liue. It is written in <hi>Geneſis</hi> the <hi>8. <hi>For the imagination of mans hart is euill euen from his youth.</hi>
               </hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 8, 21.</note> And in <hi>Iames</hi> the <hi>3.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iames. 3, 2.</note> 
               <hi>In many things wee ſinne all.</hi> And in the <hi>5.</hi> to the <hi>Galathians: <hi>The flesh luſteth againſt the ſpirit,</hi>
               </hi>
               <note place="margin">Galat. 5, 17.</note> 
               <hi>&amp; the ſpirit againſt the flesh; and theſe are contrarye one to the
<pb facs="tcp:15173:17"/>other, ſo that ye cannot do the ſame things ye would.</hi> Wée are commaunded to pray continually by Chriſt:<note place="margin">Matth. 6.</note> 
               <hi>Forgiue vs our treſpaſſes as wee forgiue them that treſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſe &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu. <hi>Do you hold it for a certaine truth that men are iuſtified onely by Chriſt, and that the works of ſanctification and newneſſe of life begun in vs, doo merit nothing concerning the worke of our ſaluation?</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> I hold it for an vndoubted truth, that the whole worke of our ſaluation is wrought in the perſon of Chriſt with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out vs, and without all reſpect of our works, either before or after repe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tance, whatſoeuer the Papiſts prate. But yet there are many places of Scripture which doo ſéeme to giue ſomething to works to the obteining of ſaluation: As the <hi>15. Pſalme;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 15. ℣ſe 1, 2, 3.</note> 
               <hi>Lord who ſhall reſt vpon thy holy mountaine: He that walketh vprightly, and worketh righteouſneſſe and ſpeaketh the truth in his hart.</hi> Againe the <hi>24. Pſalme: <hi>Who ſhall aſcend into the mountaine of the Lord, and who ſhall ſtand in his holy place,</hi>
               </hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 24. ℣ſe 3, 4.</note> 
               <hi>Euen hee that hath innocent handes and a pure hart &amp;c.</hi> Againe <hi>Eſay</hi> the <hi>33. <hi>Who
<pb facs="tcp:15173:18"/>among vs ſhal dwell with the deuouring fier,</hi>
               </hi>
               <note place="margin">Eſay. 33. ℣ſe 14, 15.</note> 
               <hi>who amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g vs ſhal dwell with the euerlaſting burnings, he that walketh in iuſtice, &amp; ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth righteous things, refuſing gaine of op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſsio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp;c.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſalm. 50, 23</note> Againe <hi>Pſalme 50. <hi>And to him that diſpoſeth his way aright will I ſhew the ſaluation of God.</hi>
               </hi>
               <note place="margin">Math. 7. ℣ſe 21, 22.</note> Again <hi>Math. 7. <hi>Not euery one that ſaith vnto me Lord, Lord, ſhall enter into the kingdome of heauen, but he that doth the will of my father which is in heauen.</hi>
               </hi> A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine <hi>Iohn 5.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iohn 5. ℣ſe 28, 29.</note> 
               <hi>For the howre ſhal come in the which al that are in the graues ſhal heare his voice &amp; they ſhall come forth, they that haue done good vnto the reſurrection of life, but they that haue done euil vnto the reſurrectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of condemnation.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 25. ℣ſe 34, 35.</note> Againe <hi>Math. 25. <hi>Come ye bleſſed of my father inherite ye the kingdome prepared for you from the beginning of the world, for I was an hungred and ye gaue me meat, I thirſted &amp; ye gaue me drinke, I was a ſtranger and ye lodged me, I was naked &amp; ye clothed me, I was ſicke &amp; ye viſited me, I was in priſon &amp; ye came vnto me.</hi>
               </hi> And there be many ſuch like. I anſwer vnto theſe pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, &amp; al ſuch like in the ſcripture (which anſwer if it be marked of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſimple, may be a keie vnto them to open much of the Scripture, and may inable them to ſtop
<pb facs="tcp:15173:18"/>the Papiſts mouths,) that theſe places doo not ſet downe &amp; expreſſe the cauſes of ſaluation, and of eternall life: but de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe &amp; point out who they be that ſhal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>be ſaued, by the effects that follow faith, &amp; repentance. The Apoſtle termeth good works the fruits, not the cauſes of righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſnes in the <hi>1.</hi> to the <hi>Philippia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Philip. 1, 11.</note> wher be praieth that they may be filled with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fruits of righteouſnes,<note place="margin">The end of good workes the glory of God.</note> which are by Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt to the glory of God. But whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Scripture ſetteth downe the cauſes of ſaluation, &amp; why men are ſaued, &amp; ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teine eternall life, it giueth all to Chriſt Ieſus. As by theſe places following, and many ſuch like, &amp; none to the contrary appeareth. <hi>Acts 4.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Acts. 4. ℣ſe 11, 12.</note> 
               <hi>This is the ſtone caſt aſide of you builders which is the head of the cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, neither is the ſaluation in any other, for among men there is giue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> none other name vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der heauen wherby we muſt be ſaued. <hi>Hebr.</hi>
               </hi> the <hi>7.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hebr. 7, 25.</note> 
               <hi>But this man</hi> (meaning Chriſt) <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he endureth euer, hath an euerlaſting prieſthood. Wherefore he is able perfectly to ſaue them that come vnto God by him, ſeeing he euer liueth to make interceſsion for vs. <hi>Hebrews</hi>
               </hi> the <hi>10.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hebr. 10, 14.</note> 
               <hi>For with one offring hath he co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſecrated for euer the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that are ſanctified.
<pb facs="tcp:15173:19"/>
                  <hi>Hebrews</hi>
               </hi> the <hi>9.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hebr. 9.28.</note> 
               <hi>So Chriſt was once offered to take away the ſinnes of many, and vnto them that looke for him ſhall he appeare the ſecond time without ſinne vnto ſaluation. <hi>Romans 3:</hi>
               </hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 3.</note> 
               <hi>To him that worketh the wages is not imputed of fauour, but of debt, but to him that worketh not, but beleeueth in him that iuſtifieth the vngodly, his faith is coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted for righteouſnes.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Epheſ. 2. ℣ſe 8, 9.</note> 
               <hi>Epheſians</hi> the <hi>2. <hi>For by grace are ye ſaued through faith &amp; that not of your ſelues, it is the gift of God, not of works that me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> may boaſt.</hi> Philippia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s 3. Paul</hi> ſaith,<note place="margin">Philipp. 3.</note> 
               <hi>Touching the righteouſneſſe that is in the lawes I was vnrebukeable:</hi>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">℣ſe </seg>6,</label> 
               <hi>But the things that were vantage vnto me,</hi>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">℣ſe </seg>7,</label>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">℣ſe </seg>8,</label> 
               <hi>the ſame I coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted loſſe for Chriſts ſake:</hi>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">℣ſe </seg>9,</label> 
               <hi>yea doubtles, I think all things but loſſe,</hi>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">℣ſe </seg>10</label> 
               <hi>for the excellent know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge ſake of Chriſt Ieſus my Lord, for whom I haue counted all things loſſe, and do iudge them to be but dunge, that I might win Chriſt and might be found in him, that is, not hauing mine owne righteouſnes which is by the law, but that which is through the faith of Chriſt eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the righteouſnes which is of God through faith, &amp;c.</hi> And the Scriptures are almoſt infinit that make to this purpoſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu. <hi>What meaneth this phraſe of ſpeach ſo much vſed in Scripture we are
<pb facs="tcp:15173:19"/>iuſtified by faith?</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> It meaneth nothing elſe, but that God accompteth and acknowledgeth vs for righteous and holy in Chriſt (in whome, as the Apoſtle ſaith in the firſt of the ſecond Epiſtle to the <hi>Corinthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,</hi> all the promiſes of God are yea, and Amen,) whom we lay hold on by faith, and applie vnto our ſoules againſt all terrors of ſinne, death, and damnation,<note place="margin">Roman. 5.</note> and ſo haue peace with God,<note place="margin">℣ſe 1, 2.</note> who hath ſaid from heauen that in him he is well pleaſed.<note place="margin">Matth. 3.17.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu. <hi>Now ſeing there is ſuch aboun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of ſaluation in Chriſt, why do not all lay hold of it?</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>An. <hi>No man</hi>
               </hi> (ſaith Chriſt) <hi>commeth vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to mee except my father draw him.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iohn. 6, 44.</note>
               <note place="margin">Iohn. 6, 37.</note> And againe he ſaith in the tenth of <hi>Iohn: <hi>But yee beleeue not:</hi>
               </hi>
               <note place="margin">Iohn. 10, 26:</note> 
               <hi>for yee are not of my ſheepe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu. <hi>Now ſeing none can be ſaued but thoſe that haue repe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tance towards God, and faith towards our Lord Ieſus Chriſt, tell me how a man may know certainely that he hath faith and Repentance?</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> If he can ſay in true féeling, <hi>The good that I would doo that I doo not,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 7, 19.</note> 
               <hi>and
<pb facs="tcp:15173:20"/>the euill that I would not doo, that I doo,</hi> with <hi>Paule</hi> in the <hi>7.</hi> to the <hi>Romans,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Math. 5.</note> and mourne vnder the burden of his ſinne.</p>
            <p>If he delite in the lawe of God in the inner man.<note place="margin">Rom. 8, 16.</note>
            </p>
            <p>If he be led by the ſpirit of God.<note place="margin">Rom. 8, 14.</note>
            </p>
            <p>If he haue crucified the fleſh with the affections of the fleſh.<note place="margin">Galat. 5, 24.</note>
            </p>
            <p>If he walke according to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> rule of a new creature,<note place="margin">Galat. 6, 15.</note> &amp; be a new creature, peace ſhal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>be vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> him, &amp; mercie, as ſaith y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Apoſtle.</p>
            <p>If he can ſay with the Apoſtle,<note place="margin">2. Cor. 1, 12.</note> 
               <hi>This is my reioycing the teſtimonie of my co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, that in ſimplicitie, &amp; godly purenes, and not in fleſhly wiſedome, but by the grace of God, I haue had my conuerſation in the world.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If hée haue true loue towardes the brethren, euen to be gréeued in their griefes, and ioyfull in their good: and carefull to helpe them in chriſtian com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion, by eaſing their gréeues, and fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thering their good; it is a true marke of the child of God. And <hi>thereby</hi> (ſaith <hi>Iohn</hi>) <hi>we know that we are of the truth,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Iohn. 3.19</note> 
               <hi>and shall before him</hi> (that is God) <hi>aſſure our harts.</hi> And in <hi>1. Iohn. 4.</hi> he ſaith: <hi>Herby we know that he dwelleth in vs, and we in him, becauſe he hath giuen vs of his ſpirit,</hi> that is
<pb facs="tcp:15173:20"/>the fruits of his ſpirit.<note place="margin">Roman. 8.</note> And if any haue not the fruits of the ſpirit the ſame is none of his. <hi>The fruits of the ſpirit are,</hi> as appeareth in <hi>Galathians 5. <hi>loue, ioy peace,</hi>
               </hi>
               <note place="margin">Galat. 5, 22.</note> 
               <hi>long ſuffering, gentlenes, goodnes, faith meek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, &amp;c.</hi> If a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by theſe notes examine himſelfe he may iudge of his repenta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce. If any man haue not repented he is di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligently to attend vpon the holy mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry of the law &amp; the goſpel that he may be called in Gods good time.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu. <hi>How may Gods people know a faithfull man?</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> By <hi>3.</hi> marks ſpecially. Firſt by his profeſſing &amp; frequenting of the publike worſhip of God, when it may be had. As in <hi>Romans 10.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 10, 9.</note> 
               <hi>For if thou shalt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſe with thy mouth the Lord Ieſus, &amp; beleeue with thy hart that God raiſed him from the dead, thou shalt be ſaued.</hi> And in <hi>1. Peter. 3.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Pet. 3.15.</note> 
               <hi>Be redie al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies to giue an anſwer to euery ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth you a reaſon of that hope that is in you.</hi> Our ſauiour Chriſt ſaith in <hi>Iohn. 8. <hi>He that is of God heareth Gods word.</hi>
               </hi>
               <note place="margin">Iohn. 8, 47.</note> Second<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly by his honeſt &amp; godly conuerſation a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g men: for <hi>Paule</hi> ſaith,<note place="margin">2. Tim. 2.</note> 
               <hi>The Lord know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth who are his,</hi>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">℣ſe </seg>15</label> 
               <hi>&amp; let euery one that nameth the name of Chrſt departe from iniquitie.
<pb facs="tcp:15173:21"/>Shew me</hi> (ſaith <hi>Iames</hi> in the ſecond of his Epiſtle) <hi>thy faith by thy works,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iames. 2, 18.</note> 
               <hi>and I will ſhewe thee my faith by my workes.</hi> Where he plainely ſheweth, that if good works be away,<note place="margin">Matth. 7.</note> there is no faith. <hi>Yee ſhall know them</hi> (ſaith Chriſt) <hi>by their fruit,</hi>
               <note place="margin">verſe, 16, 20.</note> 
               <hi>for a good tree bringeth foorth good fruit, &amp;c.</hi> Thirdly by true Chriſtian loue:<note place="margin">Iohn. 13, 35.</note> 
               <hi>Hereby</hi> (ſaith Chriſt in the <hi>13.</hi> of <hi>Iohn</hi>) <hi>shall all men know that ye are my diſciples if ye haue loue one to an other.</hi> Theſe are thrée ſure markes to know a faithfull man by ſo farre as man may iudge. Hypocrites God will either diſplay in this world in time, by bringing their ſinnes abroad to the view of all men, as he did <hi>Symon Magus</hi> his ſinnes, <hi>Iudas, Saules,</hi> and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny others, or elſe when the ſecrets of all mens harts ſhalbe diſcloſed, he will throwe thoſe tares into vnquenchable fier with others prepared to condemna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu <hi>How may a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> know an vnfaith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full man and an infidell?</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> By his life vnreformed, &amp; conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuance in his wickednes after he is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buked, &amp; heareth how he ought to walke.<note place="margin">Luke. 6. verſe 43, 44.</note> 
               <hi>It is not a good tree</hi> (ſaith Chriſt in the
<pb facs="tcp:15173:21"/>ſixt of <hi>Luke</hi>) <hi>which bringeth foorth euill fruit, neither an euil tree that bringeth forth good fruite.</hi> Againe, <hi>Iohn</hi> ſaith in his firſt epiſtle and third chapiter:<note place="margin">1, Iohn, 3, 10.</note> 
               <hi>In this are the children of God knowne, and the children of the deuill, whoſoeuer doth not righteouſneſſe is not of God.</hi> And againe, <hi>He that commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth ſinne is of the deuill. <hi>Prouerbes 29.</hi> Hee that hardeneth his necke when he is rebuked,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Prou. 29, 1.</note> 
               <hi>ſhall ſodainly be deſtroied, and cannot bee cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red. <hi>Pſalme 68.</hi> Surely God will wound the head of his enemies,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 68, 21.</note> 
               <hi>and the hairy pate of him that walketh in his ſinne.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu. <hi>Now ſhew what ioyes are prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>for true Chriſtians?</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> Such as (ſaith the Apoſtle in the ſecond chapiter of the former Epiſtle to the <hi>Corinthians</hi>) <hi>The eye hath not ſeene,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1, Cor, 2, 9.</note> 
               <hi>nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the eare heard, neyther the heart of man conceiued, prepared by God for them that loue him. <hi>Peter</hi>
               </hi> in the fift of his firſt Epiſtle, tearmeth thoſe ioyes the incorruptible crowne of glory. In the <hi>21.</hi> of the <hi>Reuela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1, Peter 5, 4.</note>
               <note place="margin">Reuel, 21, ℣, 10, 11, 12, 13 14, 15, 16, 17 18, 19, 20, 21 22, 23, 24, 25.</note> this ioy is deſcribed in the deſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of newe Ieruſalem, buylded of gold pretious ſtones, and pearles, &amp;c. where, by moſt excellent earthly things is ſette foorth the excellencie of thoſe thinges,
<pb facs="tcp:15173:22"/>which paſſe and excéede mans capacitie. Wherfore let none of vs be a prophane perſon as was <hi>Eſau,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hebr. 12, 16.</note> to ſell our birth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right for a meſſe of pottage, and for the pleaſures of the doonghill of this world, which endure but for a ſeaſon, to looſe the ioyes and dainties of heauen, which are eternall. Which thing God graunt vnto vs for his Chriſt his ſake, to whom with the Father and the Holy Ghoſt, thrée perſons &amp; one onely God, King of kinges, and Lorde of lordes, who onelie hath immortalitie, and dwelleth in the light that no man can attaine vnto, whom neuer man ſawe, ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther can ſée, be honour and power euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtingly, <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>The ende of the Catechiſme.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:15173:22"/>
            <head>To the Chriſtian Reader.</head>
            <p>BEcauſe this Catechiſme is verye ſhort, I thought it needfull to adde and adioyne vnto the ende thereof (good Reader) certeine duties requy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by God at the handes of his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, to be performed vnder payne of damnation, and the teſtimonies of Scripture which proue the ſame. For ſurely this naughtye age in perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance of dutie is verie remiſſe &amp; vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toward, perſwaded, as it ſeemeth, that a meere profeſſion of Religion with the lippe is Chriſtianity inough. And what is the ſpeeches of the moſt part of men in theſe dayes when they are blamed for their vngodly life, but theſe &amp; ſuch like? VVhy, God is mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciful, men cannot be ſaints and angels, you are ouer preciſe &amp; pure.<note place="margin">Luke 1, ℣ſe 74, 75.</note> As if it were not written that we are therfore deliuered by Chriſt from our ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, Hell, Death, and Damnation, that wee ſhoulde ſerue God without feare all the daies of our life in holines
<pb facs="tcp:15173:23"/>and righteouſnes before him, and in another place that wee ſhould liue ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berly,<note place="margin">Tim. 2, ℣ſe 12.</note> righteouſly, and godlye in this preſente worlde. And in another place: That if anye bee in Chriſt, hee muſt be a new creature.<note place="margin">2, Cor, 5.</note> And againe: Follow peace with all men,<note place="margin">Heb, 12.</note> and holy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, without the which no man ſhal ſee the Lorde. And to the ſame effecte there are infinite teſtimonies of holie Scripture. But I would ſuche mocke-gods were once mindfull of their wofull ſtate, which maye rather bee tearmed incarnate Diuels then Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, or members of the holy bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of Chriſt, ſo long as they continue ſo deſperately nought. I would (good reader) either thine or mine admoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion might doe ſome of them good. Farewell in Chriſt, and let vs pray in the ſpirit, for the peace and proſperity of Zion, &amp; our gratious Souereigne.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Thine in Chriſt, Th. Settle.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="treatise">
            <pb facs="tcp:15173:23"/>
            <head>A fardle of Chriſtian <hi>du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, needful to be taken vp and borne</hi> of all ſuch as trauaile towards eternall life according as euery of their callings require.</head>
            <div n="1" type="part">
               <head>1. That all Chriſtian men and women are bound to go to Church, or the place appointed for Gods worſhip, namely where Gods word is prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched, praiers and Sacraments mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtred: &amp; to ioyne themſelues in fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowſhip in thoſe holy exerciſes of religion, that ſo they may growe vp in true Chriſtianitie.</head>
               <p>BVt yee ſhall ſéeke the place which the Lorde your God ſhall chooſe out of all your tribes,<note place="margin">Deut, 12, verſe 5.</note> to put his name there and there to dwel, &amp; thither thou ſhalt come. This place was vnder the lawe <hi>Ieruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem,</hi> or where Gods Arke and taberna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle was pitched. And now ſince Chriſtes birth, is all places of the worlde where Gods word and ſacramentes are truely preached and miniſtred.</p>
               <p>It ſhall be in the laſt dayes,<note place="margin">Eſay 2, ver, 2.</note> that the mountains of the houſe of the Lord ſhal be prepared in the top of the mountains,
<pb facs="tcp:15173:24"/>and ſhall bée exalted aboue the hilles, and all nations ſhall flowe vnto it. And And many people ſhall go &amp; ſay:<note place="margin">Micha, 4, 1.</note> Come, and lette vs goe vp to the mountaine of the Lorde to the houſe of the God of Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob, and hee will teach vs his wayes, and we will walke in his pathes.</p>
               <p>And they that dwell in one Citie ſhall goe vnto an other,<note place="margin">Zachar. 8, ℣. 21, 22.</note> ſaying: Vp, let vs goe and pray before the Lorde,<note place="margin">One muſt prouoke, an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other to go to the aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bli<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s.</note> and ſeeke the Lord of hoſtes: I will go alſo. Yea, great people and mightie nations ſhall come to ſéeke the Lord of hoſtes in Ieruſalem, and to pray before the Lord.</p>
               <p>Bleſſed is the man whoſe ſtrength is in thée,<note place="margin">Pſal, 84, ℣ſe 5, 6, 7.</note> &amp; whoſe heart are in thy wayes. They going through the vale of Baca make welles therein, &amp;c. They go from ſtrength to ſtrength, till euerie one ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare before God in Zion. Then a ſhower of rayne ought not to bee an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe for any to abſent himſelfe from the holie aſſemblies, as many a one of our daintie Chriſtians doe in theſe dayes make it.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>2. Examples of the meetings of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians
<pb facs="tcp:15173:24"/>for the hearing of the word, prayer, and adminiſtration of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>ANd they continued in the Apoſtles doctrine, and fellowſhip,<note place="margin">Acts, 2, 42.</note> and fellowſhip, &amp; breaking of bread, and praiers.</p>
               <p>And they continued daily with one accorde in the temple,<note place="margin">Acts 2, 46.</note> and breaking of bread at home.</p>
               <p>And daily in the temple,<note place="margin">Acts 5, 46.</note> &amp; from houſe to houſe they ceaſed not to teach and preach Ieſus Chriſt.</p>
               <p>And the next Saboth day came almoſt the whole Cittie together to heare the word of God.<note place="margin">Acts 13, 44.</note>
               </p>
               <p>And the firſt day of the wéeke the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples beeing come together to breake bread,<note place="margin">Acts 20, 7.</note> 
                  <hi>Paule</hi> preached vnto them readie to depart on the morow, &amp; continued the preaching vntill midnight.</p>
               <p>When yée come togeather therefore into one place,<note place="margin">1, Cor, 11, 20</note> this is not to eate the Lords Supper.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>3. Examples of the ſeruantes of God, reioicing to go to the aſſemblies of God, and to ſee others goe. And of
<pb facs="tcp:15173:25"/>the ſeruants of God complaining &amp; ſorrowing for the want of the holie aſſemblies, when as by perſecution they were hindered, and of their deſires to be there.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>I</hi> Reioiſed when they ſaid to me,<note place="margin">Pſal, 122, ℣ſe 1, 2.</note> we wil go into the houſe of the Lord. Our féet ſhall ſtand in thy gates, O Ieruſalem.</p>
               <p>O Lord of hoſtes how amiable are thy tabernacles.<note place="margin">Pſal, 84, verſe 1, 2, 3.</note> My ſoule longeth, yea and fainteth for the courtes of the Lorde, for my heart and my fleſh reioice in the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing God. Yea, the ſparrow hath founde her an houſe, and the ſwallow a neſt for her where ſhe may lay her young, euen by thy altars O Lord of hoſtes, my king and my God. Bleſſed are they that may dwell in thine houſe, they will euer praiſe thée.</p>
               <p>As the Hart brayeth for the riuers of water,<note place="margin">Pſal, 42, verſe 1, 2, 3, 4.</note> ſo panteth my ſoule after thée, O God. My ſoule luſteth for God, euen for the liuing God, when ſhall I come and appeare before the preſence of God. My teares haue béene my meat day &amp; night, while they daily ſay vnto me, where is thy God. Whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bred theſe things,
<pb facs="tcp:15173:25"/>I poured out my verie heart, becauſe I had gone with the multitude, and ledde them into the houſe of God, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>And he ſaid (that is <hi>Dauid</hi> vnto <hi>Saule</hi>) Wherefore doth my Lorde thus perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute his ſeruant,<note place="margin">1, Sam, 26, 18, 19.</note> for what haue I done, or what euill is in my hande. Nowe therefore I beſeech thée, lette my Lorde heare the wordes of his ſeruant. If the Lorde haue ſtirred thée vp againſt mee, lette him ſmell the ſauour of a Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice: But if the children of men haue done it, curſed be they before the Lorde. For they haue caſt mee out this day from abyding in the inheritaunce of the Lord God, ſaying: goe ſerue other Gods.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Hezekia</hi> hearing the meſſage of death from the Lorde,<note place="margin">Eſay 38. ℣ſe 1, 2, 3, 18, 19.</note> praied and wept not for feare of death, but as the whole chapiter doth euidently declare, becauſe he ſhould no longer liue to praiſe God in his ſanc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuarie, and to growe vp among the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of God in more graces to promote Gods glorie. For ſayth hee (after hee had promiſe of life) The graue cannot confeſſe thée, death cannot praiſe thée, they that goe downe into the pitte can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not
<pb facs="tcp:15173:26"/>hope for thy truth. But the liuing, the liuing hée ſhall confeſſe thée, as I doe this day: the father to the children ſhall declare thy truth.</p>
               <p>One thing haue I deſired of the Lorde that I will require,<note place="margin">Pſal, 27, 4.</note> euen that I maye dwel in the houſe of the Lord all y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> daies of my life, to behold the beauty of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lord &amp; to viſite his temple. <hi>Dauid</hi> by the beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of the Lorde in this place, meaneth neth nothing elſe but y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hearing of Gods holy word, praiers, praiſes, thankſgiuing &amp; the vſe of other Gods ceremonies for that miniſtration appointed.</p>
               <p>For a day in thy courts is better then a thouſand other where:<note place="margin">Pſal. 84, 10.</note> I had rather be a doore kéeper in the houſe of my God, then to dwell in the tabernacle of wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kednes.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="part">
               <head>4 That al muſt heare &amp; receiue Gods worde.</head>
               <p>REceiue with méekenes the word that is grafted in you,<note place="margin">Iames 1, 21.</note> which is able to ſaue your ſoules.</p>
               <p>As newe borne babes deſire the ſincere milke of the worde,<note place="margin">1, Pet 1, 2.</note> that you may growe thereby.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:15173:26"/>
               <p>He that is of God heareth Gods word:<note place="margin">Iohn 8, 47.</note> ye therefore heare them not, becauſe yee are not of God.</p>
               <p>Hee that turneth away his eare from hearing the lawe,<note place="margin">Prou. 28, 9.</note> euen his praier ſhalbe abhominable.</p>
               <p>Deſpiſe not propheſiyng.<note place="margin">1, Theſ. 5, 20 Prou. 13, 13.</note> He that deſpiſeth the word ſhall be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="part">
               <head>5 That Gods worde is effectuall, and full of power to conuert men, and to alter their mindes, and cleanſe their hartes.</head>
               <p>THe lawe of the Lorde is perfect,<note place="margin">Pſal. 19, 7.</note> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerting the ſoule.</p>
               <p>Now are ye cleane through the worde which I haue ſpoken vnto you.<note place="margin">Iohn 15, 3.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Sanctifie them with thy truth.<note place="margin">Iohn 17, 17.</note> Thy word is truth.</p>
               <p>For I am not aſhamed of the goſpel of Chriſt,<note place="margin">Rom. 1, 16.</note> for it is the power of God vnto ſaluation to euerie one that beléeueth.</p>
               <p>For the word of God is liuely,<note place="margin">Heb. 4, 12.</note> &amp; migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie in operation, &amp; ſharper then anie two edged ſword, &amp; entreth through, euen vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> diuiding a ſunder of the ſoule &amp; the ſpirite, &amp; of the ioints and the marrowe,
<pb facs="tcp:15173:27"/>and is a diſcerner of the thoughtes and the intents of the hart.</p>
               <p>Neuertheleſſe though wee walke in the fleſh,<note place="margin">2, Cor. 10. ℣. 5, 6, 7.</note> yet we war not after the fleſh. For the weapons of our warfare are not carnall, but mightie through God to caſt downe holdes, caſting downe the imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations, and euerie high thing that is exalted aboue the glorie of God, &amp; brin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging into captiuitie euery thought, to the obedience of Chriſt. And hauing rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vengeance againſt al diſobedience, when your obedience is fulfilled.</p>
               <p>Is not my worde euen like a fier, ſaith the Lord,<note place="margin">Ierem, 23, 29</note> and like an hammer that brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth the ſtone?</p>
               <p>Surely as the raine commeth downe, and the ſnowe from the heauen,<note place="margin">Eſay 55. ℣ 10, 11.</note> and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turneth not thither, but watereth the earth, and maketh it to bring foorth and bud, that it may giue ſéede to the ſower, and bread vnto him that eateth. So ſhall my word be that goeth out of my mouth, it ſhal not returne vnto me voide, but it ſhall accompliſh that which I will, and it ſhall proſper in the thing whereto I ſent it.<note place="margin">1, Cor. 14. verſ. 24, 25.</note>
               </p>
               <p>But if all propheſie, and there come in
<pb facs="tcp:15173:27"/>one that beléeueth not or one vnlearned, he is rebuked of all, and is iudged of all: and ſo are the ſecretes of his heart made manifeſt, and ſo he wil fal downe on his face, and worſhip God, and ſay plainely that God is in you indéede.</p>
               <p>Theſe places then conſidered, it will appeare that they which neglect and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſe the hearing of the worde preached, cannot be ſaued, though they truſt neuer ſo much to ſecret reuelations, they ſhall ſhall aſſoone come to heauen, as hee to Fraunce that will paſſe the ſea without a ſhippe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="part">
               <head>6 That for euerie thing that a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian man doth, hee ought to aſke councell at the worde of God, and make that the rule of al his doings.</head>
               <p>TAke héede therefore that yée doo as the Lord your God hath commanded you:<note place="margin">Deut, 5, 32.</note> turne not aſide to the right hande, nor to the left.</p>
               <p>Whatſoeuer is not of faith (that is of knowledge from the word) is ſinne.<note place="margin">Rom. 14, verſe 23.</note>
               </p>
               <p>And when they ſhall ſay vnto you, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire at them that haue a ſpirit of diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation,<note place="margin">Eſay 8. verſe 19, 20.</note> &amp; at the ſouthſayers which whiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per
<pb facs="tcp:15173:28"/>and murmur. Should not a people enquire at their God? From the liuing to the deade, to the lawe and to the teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony, if they ſpeake not according to this word: it is becauſe there is no light in them.</p>
               <p>Wo to the rebellious children (ſaith y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lord) that take councell but not of mée,<note place="margin">Eſay 30, ℣ſe 1, 2</note> &amp; couer with a couering, but not by my ſpirit, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> they may lay ſin vpon ſin, which walke foorth to goe downe into Egypt (&amp; haue not aſked at my mouth.)</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Examples of Dauid.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thy word is a lanterne vnto my féet,<note place="margin">Pſa. 119, 105</note> and a light vnto my path.</p>
               <p>Alſo thy teſtimonies are my delight,<note place="margin">Pſal. 119, 24</note> &amp; my councellers.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="part">
               <head>7 That the worde of God conteineth all things neceſſary vnto ſaluation.</head>
               <p>THe Law of the Lorde is perfect,<note place="margin">Pſal. 19, 7.</note> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerting the ſoule.</p>
               <p>And that thou haſt knowne the holie ſcriptures of a child,<note place="margin">2. Tim 3. ℣. 15, 16, 17.</note> which are able to make thée wiſe vnto ſaluatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, through y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> faith which is in Chriſt Ieſus. For the whole ſcripture is giuen by inſpiratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of God, &amp; is profitable to teach, to improue,
<pb facs="tcp:15173:28"/>to correct, &amp; to inſtruct in righteouſneſſe. That the man of God may bee abſolute, being made perfect vnto all good woorks.</p>
               <p>Receiue with méekenes the word that is grafted in you,<note place="margin">Iames 1, 21.</note> which is able to ſaue your ſoules.</p>
               <p>Search the ſcriptures,<note place="margin">Iohn 5, 39.</note> for in them yee thinke to haue eternall life.</p>
               <p>Then if eternal life &amp; ſaluation of our ſoules bee obteined by the ſcripures, and doctrine of the worde conteined therein, much good doe the Papiſtes with the reſt which they get more by the meanes of traditions and vnwritten verities.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="part">
               <head>8 Of Magiſtrates, and firſt what men are to be choſen.</head>
               <p>MOreouer, prouide thou among al the people men of courage,<note place="margin">Exod. 18.21.</note> fearing God, men dealing truly, men hating couetouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, &amp; appoint ſuch ouer the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to be rulers ouer thouſa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds, rulers ouer hundreds, &amp;c.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="part">
               <head>9 That Magiſtrates are to execute Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice vprightly towards all.</head>
               <p>ANd I charged your iudges that ſame time, ſaying:<note place="margin">Deut. 1, 16.</note> Heare the cauſes of brethren, and iudge righteouſly betwene
<pb facs="tcp:15173:29"/>euery man and his brother, &amp; the ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger that is with him, ye ſhal haue no re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of perſons, but ſhall heare the ſmall aſwell as the great: ye ſhal not feare the face of man, for the iudgment is Gods.</p>
               <p>Ye ſhal not do vniuſtly in iudgement,<note place="margin">Deuitie. 19.</note>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">verſe </seg>15</label> thou ſhalt not fanour the perſon of the poore, nor honour y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> perſon of the mighty, but thou ſhalt iudge thy neighbor iuſtly.</p>
               <p>Thou ſhalt not eſtéeme a poore man in his cauſe.<note place="margin">Exod, 23.3.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Iudges &amp; officers ſhalt thou make thée &amp;c. and they ſhall iudge the people with righteous iudgement.<note place="margin">Deut. 17, 18.</note>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="part">
               <head>10. That Iudges and magiſtrates muſt take no rewardes nor bribes, nor wreſt the Lawe.</head>
               <p>ANd he ſet iudges in the land through out all the ſtrong Cities of Iuda,<note place="margin">2. Chron. 19 verſe 5, 6, 7.</note> ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie by citie: And ſaid to the Iudges take héed what ye doe. For ye execute not the iudgements of man but of the Lord, &amp; he wil be with you in the cauſe and iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. Wherefore nowe let the feare of the Lord be vpon you, take héed and doe it: for there is no iniquitie with the Lord, neither reſpecte of perſons, nor re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiuing of reward.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:15173:29"/>
               <p>Heare this I pray you ye heads of the houſe of Iacob &amp; princes of the houſe of Iſraell,<note place="margin">Mich. 3. verſe 10, 11.</note> they abhor iudgement and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uert al equitie, they build vp Zion with bloud and Ieruſalem with iniquitie, the heads therof iudge for rewards, &amp;c: ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſhal Zion for your ſakes be plowed as a field.</p>
               <p>To make good for the euill of their hands the prince aſked,<note place="margin">Mich. 7. verſ. 3, 4.</note> &amp; the iudge iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth for a reward. Therefore the great man ſpeaketh out of the corruption of his hart, and ſo they wrap it vp, the beſt of them is like a brier, &amp; the moſt righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous is ſharper then a thorne hedge.</p>
               <p>Thou ſhalt take no gift,<note place="margin">Exod. 23, 8.</note> for the gift blindeth the wiſe, and peruerteth the words of the righteous.</p>
               <p>Wreſt not thou the lawe,<note place="margin">Deut. 16, 19.</note> neither re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect any perſon, neither take reward, for the reward blindeth the eies of the wiſe, &amp; peruerteth the words of the iuſt.</p>
               <p>Their rulers loue to ſay with ſhame bring yée.<note place="margin">Oſea, 4, 18.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Woe vnto them whiche iuſtifieth the wicked for a reward,<note place="margin">Eſay, 5, 23.</note> and taketh away the righteouſneſſe of the righteous from him. Read the <hi>82. Pſalme.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="part">
               <head>
                  <pb facs="tcp:15173:30"/>
                  <hi>11. That magiſtrates muſt puniſh the wicked, or elſe they ſhall prouoke Gods wrath againſt themſelues, and be a cauſe to increaſe ſinne.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>A Wiſe king ſcattereth the wicked,<note place="margin">Prou. 20, 26</note> &amp; cauſeth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whéele to turne ouer them. For Princes are not to be feared for good workes,<note place="margin">Rom 13. ℣ſe 3, 4.</note> but for euill, wilt thou bée without feare of the power? doo well, ſo ſhalt thou haue praiſe of the ſame, for he is the miniſter of God for thy welth: but if thou do euill, feare; for he beareth not the ſword for nought, for he is the mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter of God to take vengeance on him that dooth euill.</p>
               <p>Becauſe ſentence againſt an euill worke is not executed ſpéedily,<note place="margin">Eccleſ. 8, 10.</note> therefore the hart of the children of men is fully ſet in them to do euill.</p>
               <p>Neither will I be with you any more except ye deſtroy the exco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>municate from among you.<note place="margin">Ioſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. 7, 12.</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Examples.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I put on iuſtice,<note place="margin">Iob 29. verſe 14, 15.</note> and it couered me, my iudgement was as a robe &amp; a crowne. I was the eies of the blind, and I was the féet to the lame: I was a father vnto the poore, and when I knew not the cauſe I
<pb facs="tcp:15173:30"/>ſought it out diligently, I brake alſo the iawes of the vnrighteous, and plucked the pray out of his téeth.</p>
               <p>Betimes will I deſtroy al the wicked of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> land,<note place="margin">Pſal. 101, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> that I may cut of al y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> workers of iniquitie from the citie of the Lord.</p>
               <p>Thus ſaith the Lord,<note place="margin">1. Kings. 20. ℣ſe 42.</note> becauſe thou <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hab</hi> haſt let go out of thine hands a man (that is <hi>Benhadad</hi> king of <hi>Aram</hi>) whom I appointed to die, thy life ſhall go for his life, and thy people for his people. A worthie example to be noted of all ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates, that they may not ſpare &amp; foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhly pittie Idolaters and vile ſinners, whom God in his law commaundeth to be ſlaine.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="part">
               <head>12. That princes, magiſtrates, and men in authoritie ought to be religious, &amp; mainteiners and nurſers of reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, and take eſpeciall delight in thoſe that feare God.</head>
               <p>BE wiſe now therefore yée kings,<note place="margin">Pſal. 10. ℣ſe 11, 12.</note> be learned ye iudges of the earth, ſerue the Lord in feare, and reioyce in trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling. Kiſſe the ſonne leaſt he be angrie &amp; ye periſh in the way, when his wrath ſhall ſuddenly burne.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:15173:31"/>
               <p>And when he (that is the king) ſhal ſit vpon the throne of his kingdome,<note place="margin">Deut. 17. ℣ſe 18, 19.</note> then ſhall he write him this law, repeated in a booke by the prieſts of the <hi>Leuits,</hi> and it ſhalbe with him, and he ſhall read ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in all the daies of his life, that he may learne to feare the Lord his God, and to kéepe all the wordes of this law, &amp; theſe ordinances for to do them. That his hart be not lifted vp aboue his brethren, and that he turne not from the commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to the right hand or to the left, but that he may prolong his daies in his kingdome, he, &amp; his ſonnes in the midſt of Iſraell.</p>
               <p>Let not this booke (the Lords words to <hi>Ioſua</hi> &amp; in his perſon to all magiſtrates) of this law depart out of thy mouth but meditate therin day and night,<note place="margin">Ioſua. 1, 8.</note> that thou maiſt obſerue &amp; do according to all that is written therein. For then ſhalt thou make thy way proſperous, &amp; then ſhalt thou haue good ſucceſſe.</p>
               <p>Thou (that is the Church) ſhall ſucke the milke of the Gentiles,<note place="margin">Eſay. 60, 16.</note> &amp; ſhalt ſucke the breſts of Kings, &amp; thou ſhalt know that I the Lord am thy ſauiour.</p>
               <p>Kings ſhalbe,<note place="margin">Eſay. 49, ℣ſe 23, 24.</note> thy (that is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> churches)
<pb facs="tcp:15173:31"/>nurſing fathers and quéenes thy nurſes, they ſhall worſhip thée with their faces towards the earth, and licke vp the duſt of thy féet, and thou ſhalt knowe that I am the Lord.</p>
               <p>In the <hi>Reuelation</hi> it is written:<note place="margin">Reue. 21, 24</note> That the kings of the earth ſhall bring their glorie &amp; honour vnto the new Ieruſale<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Example of Dauid.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>O my ſoule,<note place="margin">Pſalm. 16.2.</note> thou haſt ſaid vnto the Lord thou art my Lord, my well doing extendeth not to thée: but to the Saints that are in the earth, &amp; to the excellent: all my delight is in them.</p>
               <p>I am a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>panion of al them that feare thée and kéepe thy precepts.<note place="margin">Pſal. 119, 63,</note>
               </p>
               <p>Mine eies ſhalbe vnto the faithfull of the land that they may dwell with me,<note place="margin">Pſal. 101, 6.</note> he that walketh in a perfect way he ſhal ſerue me.</p>
               <p>When I remembred theſe things I powred out my very hart,<note place="margin">Pſal. 42, 4.</note> becauſe I had gone with the multitude &amp; led them into the houſe of God.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>13. That all ſubiects are to obey their princes, and thoſe that are appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted vnder them, that is inferior ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrats in all things, not contrarie
<pb facs="tcp:15173:32"/>to the commandements of God, &amp; to pay them tributes.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>LEt euery ſoule be ſubiect vnto the higher powers:<note place="margin">Rom. 13. ℣ſe 1, 2, 3.</note> for there is no power but of God: whoſoeuer therfore reſiſteth the power, reſiſteth the ordinance of God, and they that reſiſt ſhall receiue to themſelues iudgement. For princes are not to be feared for good workes, but for euill, wilt thou then be without feare of the power? do well, ſo ſhalt thou haue praiſe of the ſame, &amp;c. wherefore ye muſt be ſubiect, not becauſe of wrath only, but alſo for co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcience ſake. For this cauſe ye pay alſo tribute, for they are Gods mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters, applying themſelues for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame thing. Giue to all men therfore their du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, tribute to whom ye owe tribute: cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome to whom cuſtome, feare to whom feare, honour to whom ye owe honour.</p>
               <p>Put them in remembrance that they be ſubiect to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> principalities &amp; powers,<note place="margin">Titus. 3, 1.</note> and that they be obedient and readie to euery good worke.</p>
               <p>Submit your ſelues vnto all maner ordinance of man for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lords ſake,<note place="margin">1. Peter. 2. ℣ſe 13, 14.</note> whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it be to the king as vnto the ſuperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, or vnto gouernours as vnto them
<pb facs="tcp:15173:32"/>that are ſent of him, for the puniſhment of euill doers, and for the praiſe of them that do well.</p>
               <p>Honour al men,<note place="margin">1. Pet. 3.17.</note> loue brotherly fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip: feare God honour the king.</p>
               <p>Giue vnto Ceſar,<note place="margin">Math. 22, 21</note> the things whiche are Ceſars, and giue vnto GOD thoſe things which are Gods.</p>
               <p>And when they were come to <hi>Caper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naum</hi> they y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> receiued polle money came to <hi>Peter</hi> &amp; ſaid,<note place="margin">Math. 17. ℣ſ. 24, 25, 26, 27.</note> doth not your maſter pay tribute, He ſaid yes. And when he was come into the houſe Jeſus preuented him, ſaying: what thinkeſt thou <hi>Simon?</hi> of whom doo the kings of the earth take tribute or polle money? of their children or of ſtrangers? <hi>Peter</hi> ſaid vnto him of ſtrangers: the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſaid Ieſus vnto him, then are the children frée. Neuertheleſſe leaſt we ſhould offend them, go to the ſea and caſt in an angle, and take the firſt fiſhe that commeth vp, and when thou haſt o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened his mouth thou ſhalt find a péece of twentie pence, that take, and giue it to them for thée and mée.</p>
               <p>And the king ſaid to his ſergea<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts that ſtood about him,<note place="margin">1. Sam. 22, 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> turne &amp; ſlay the prieſts of the Lord, becauſe their hand alſo
<pb facs="tcp:15173:33"/>is with <hi>Dauid,</hi> and becauſe they knew when he fled and ſhewed it not to mée. But the ſeruants of the king would not moue their hand to fall vpon the prieſts of the Lord.</p>
               <p>And when they had brought them they ſet them before the Councel,<note place="margin">Acts. 4. verſe 27, 28, 29.</note> &amp; the chiefe prieſt aſked them, ſaying: did not wée ſtraightly co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maund you that you ſhould not teach in this manner &amp;c? Then <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> &amp; the Apoſtles anſwered &amp; ſaid, wée ought rather to obey God then men.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="part">
               <head>14. That none ought to curſe or vſe railing or euill ſpeaches of magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates.</head>
               <p>CVrſe not the king,<note place="margin">Eccleſ. 10, 20</note> no not in thy thought, neither curſſe the rich in thy bed chamber, for the foule of heauen ſhal carrie the voice, and that whiche hath wings ſhall declare the matter.</p>
               <p>Thou ſhalt not raile vpon the iudges,<note place="margin">Exod. 22, 28.</note> neither ſpeake euill of the ruler of the people.</p>
               <p>Likewiſe notwithſtanding the drea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers alſo defile the fleſh,<note place="margin">Iud. 8.</note> and diſpiſe go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernment, and ſpeake euil of them that are in authoritie. Yet <hi>Michaell</hi> the ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>changell, &amp;c.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:15173:33"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Example of Paule.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I am not mad <hi>ô</hi> noble <hi>Feſtus,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Acts. 26, 29.</note> but I ſpeake the words of truth and ſobernes. Yet none of theſe things do let why the miniſters of Gods word ſhuld not after the example of <hi>Iohn Baptiſt</hi> to <hi>Herod,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mark. 6. 1. Kings. 21. ℣ſe 20.</note> &amp; <hi>Elias</hi> to <hi>Ahab,</hi> &amp; others of Gods ſeruants to other magiſtrats, if néed require, ſharp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly reproue them when they ſwarue fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> godlineſſe and become wicked.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="part">
               <head>15. That good princes and magiſtrats are taken away, and an alteration of ſtates often made becauſe of the ſinne and wickednes of the people.</head>
               <p>FOr the tranſgreſſion of a land there are many princes thereof,<note place="margin">Prou. 28.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </note> but by a man of vnderſtanding and knowledge a realme likewiſe endureth long.</p>
               <p>For lo,<note place="margin">Eſay 3 ℣ſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 2, 3, 4.</note> the Lord God of hoſts will take away from Ieruſalem and from <hi>Iudah</hi> the ſtay and the ſtrength: euen all the ſtay of bread, and all the ſtay of water. The ſtrong man and the man of warre, the iudge and the prophet, the prudent and the aged, the capteine of ſif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie and the honorable, and the counceller and the cunning artificer, and I will ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>point
<pb facs="tcp:15173:34"/>children to be their princes, and babes ſhall rule ouer them.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="part">
               <head>16. That the miniſters and paſtors of the Church ought diligently to ſeede their flockes and teach their people, vnder paine of damnation, and that faithfully without chop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping and changing.</head>
               <p>ANd of <hi>Leui</hi> he ſaid,<note place="margin">Deut. 33, 10.</note> let thy <hi>Thummin</hi> &amp; thy <hi>Vrin</hi> be with thy holy one, &amp;c. They ſhall teach <hi>Iacob</hi> thy iudgements and Iſraell thy law: they ſhall put in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſe before thy face.</p>
               <p>And they (that is the <hi>Leuites</hi>) read in the booke of the law of GOD diſtinct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,<note place="margin">Nehem. 8.8.</note> and gaue the ſenſe, and cauſed them (that is the people) is vnderſtand the reading.</p>
               <p>O Sonne of man I haue made thée a watchman vnto the houſe of Iſraell,<note place="margin">Ezech. 33. ℣ſ,, 9.</note> therefore thou ſhalt heare the word at my mouth, and admoniſh them from me. When I ſhall ſay vnto the wicked man, O wicked man thou ſhalt die the death: if thou doeſt not ſpeake and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniſh the wicked of his way, the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked man ſhall die for his iniquitie, but
<pb facs="tcp:15173:34"/>his bloud will I require at thy hands. Neuertheloſſe if thou warne the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked of his way to turne from it, if he do not turne from his way he ſhall die for his iniquitie, but thou haſt deliuered thy ſoule.</p>
               <p>Take héed vnto your ſelues and to all the flocke,<note place="margin">Acts, 20, 28.</note> whereof the Holy ghoſt hath made you the ouerſeers, to féede the church of God, which he hath purchaſed with his owne bloud.</p>
               <p>I charge thée therfore before God,<note place="margin">2. Timoth. 4 verſe 1, 2.</note> and before the Lord Ieſus Chriſt which ſhal iudge the quicke and the dead, at his ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearing and in his kingdome, Preach the word, be inſtant in ſeaſon and out of ſeaſon, improue, rebuke, exhort, with all long ſuffering and doctrine.</p>
               <p>The Elders which are amongſt you,<note place="margin">1. Pet. 5. verſe 1.2.</note> I beſéech which am alſo an Elder, &amp;c. Féed the flocke of GOD that dependeth vpon you, caring for it not by co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtraint, but willingly; not for filthie lucre, but of a readie mind, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Let a man ſo thinke of vs as of the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters of Chriſt,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 4. ℣. 1, 2.</note> and diſpoſers of the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crets of God, and as for the reſt, it is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired of the diſpoſers that euery man
<pb facs="tcp:15173:35"/>be found faithfull.</p>
               <p>The Prophet that hath a dreame let him tell a dreame,<note place="margin">Iere. 23, 28.</note> and he that hath my word let him ſpeake my word faithful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, for what is the chaffe to the wheat ſaith the Lord?</p>
               <p>Therefore ſéeing wée haue receiued this miniſtration,<note place="margin">2. Corint. 4. ℣ſe 1, 2.</note> as wée haue receiued mercie, we ſaint not, but haue eaſt of the clokes of ſhame, and walke not in craf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tineſſe, neither handle wée the word of God deceitfully: but in declaration of the truth we approue our ſelues to eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry mans conſcience in the ſight of God.</p>
               <p>For we are not as many which make marchandize of the word of God,<note place="margin">2. Cor. 2.17.</note> but as of ſinceritie, but as of God in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſight of God ſpeake we in Chriſt. O I would to God that all our miniſters could thus in truth ſpeake.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="17" type="part">
               <head>17. That miniſters and paſtours ought to be examples to their flockes in holy conuerſation and godly life, otherwiſe they are a ſlander to the miniſtrie.</head>
               <p>BE vnto them that beléeue an example in word,<note place="margin">1. Tim. 4.12</note> in conuerſation, in loue, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpirit,
<pb facs="tcp:15173:35"/>in faith, and in patience.</p>
               <p>In all things ſhew thy ſelfe an exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of good workes,<note place="margin">Titus 2, 7.</note> with vnedrrupt doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine, with grauitie and integritie, and with the, wholeſome word which cannot be condemned, that he which withſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth may be aſhamed, hauing nothing conrerning you to ſpeake euill of.</p>
               <p>Féed the flocke of God,<note place="margin">1. Pet. 5, 3.</note> &amp;c. That ye may be examples to the flocke.</p>
               <p>Ye are witneſſes and God alſo (ſaith <hi>Paule</hi>) how holily, iuſtly,<note place="margin">1. Theſſ. 2. ℣ſe 10.</note> and vnblame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ablely, wée behaued our ſelues among you that beléeue.</p>
               <p>We giue none occaſion of offence in any thing that our miniſtrie ſhould not be reprehended.<note place="margin">2. Cor. 4.6.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Brethren, be ye followers of me,<note place="margin">Philip. 3. ℣ſe 17, 18.</note> and looke on them whiche walke ſo, as you haue vs for an example. For many walke of whom I haue told you often, &amp; now tell you wéeping, that they are the enimies of the croſſe of Chriſt, whoſe end is damnation, whoſe God is their belly, &amp; whoſe glorie is to their ſhame which mind earthly things.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="18" type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>18. That the paſtors and miniſters of Gods word are to bee eſteemed
<pb facs="tcp:15173:36"/>greatly of, to be reuerenced, and to be obeyed in their meſſage, other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe reproch is offered to God.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>LEt a man ſo thinke of vs,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 4 1.</note> as of the miniſters of Chriſt, and diſpoſers of the ſecretes of God.</p>
               <p>How bewtifull are the féete of them that bring glad tidings of peace,<note place="margin">Rom. 10, 15</note> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> bring glad tidings of good things.</p>
               <p>Now we beſéech you brethren that ye acknowledge them,<note place="margin">1. Theſ. 5. verſe 12, 13.</note> which labour amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g you, and are ouer you in the Lord, and admoniſh you, that ye haue them in ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular loue, for their workes ſake.</p>
               <p>Obey them that haue the ouerſight of you,<note place="margin">Hebr. 13, 17<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </note> and ſubmit your ſelues, for they watch for your ſoules: as they that muſt giue accompts, that they may do it with ioy and not with griefe, for that is vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>profitable for you.</p>
               <p>Verely,<note place="margin">Iohn. 13, 20.</note> verely I ſay vnto you, if I ſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d any, he that receiueth him receiueth me: and he that receiueth me receiueth him that ſent me.</p>
               <p>He that heareth you heareth me,<note place="margin">Luke. 10, 16.</note> and he that diſpiſeth you diſpiſeth me: and he that diſpiſeth me diſpiſeth him that ſent me.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:15173:36"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Example.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And the trial of one which was in my fleſh, ye diſpiſed not neither abhored,<note place="margin">Gal. 4.14.</note> but ye receiued me as an angell of God, yea as Chriſt Ieſus.</p>
               <p>Receiue him therefore (that is <hi>Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phroditus</hi>) in the Lord with all gladnes,<note place="margin">Philip, 2, 29.</note> and make much of ſuch.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="19" type="part">
               <head>19. That the people or pariſhes which haue Gods word preached, dilige<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly &amp; faithfully vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, are bound in conſcience, liberally to ſuſteine and nouriſh thoſe that preach vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</head>
               <p>BEware that y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> forſake not the <hi>Leuite,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Deut. 12, 19.</note> as long as thou liueſt vpon the earth. The <hi>Leuits</hi> were appointed to teach the people, which came of <hi>Leui</hi> Iacobs ſon.<note place="margin">Deut. 33, 10.</note>
               </p>
               <p>And into whatſoeuer houſe ye enter firſt,<note place="margin">Luke 10, ver. 5, 6, 7.</note> ſay peace be to this houſe, &amp;c. &amp; in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> houſe tarrie ſtill eating &amp; drinking ſuch things as ſhalbe ſet before you by them: for the laborer is worthie of his wages.</p>
               <p>My defe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> examine me is this:<note place="margin">1. Cor. 9. ver. 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 11, 12, 13, 14.</note> haue we not power to lead about a wife being a ſiſter, as wel as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> reſt of the Apoſtles, &amp; as brethren of the Lord and
<pb facs="tcp:15173:37"/>
                  <hi>Cephas?</hi> or I onely &amp; <hi>Barnabas</hi> haue not we power not to worke? who goeth a warfare any time at his owne coſt? &amp;c. If we haue ſowne vnto you ſpirituall things, is it a great thing if we reape your carnal things? Do ye not know that they which miniſter about y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holy things eat of the things of the temples? &amp; they which the altar? ſo alſo hath the Lord or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deined that they which preach the goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell ſhould liue of the goſpell.</p>
               <p>The elders that rule wel are worthy double honour,<note place="margin">1. Timoth. 5. ℣ſe 17, 18.</note> (that is double reward) ſpecially they which labour in the word &amp; doctrine. For the Scripture ſaith, thou ſhalt not moſel the mouth of the are that treadeth out the corne, the labourer is worthie of his wages.</p>
               <p>Let him that is taught in the word,<note place="margin">Galath. 6.7.</note> make him that teacheth him partaker of all his goods, be not deceiued God is not mocked.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="20" type="part">
               <head>20. That the not hauing or to bee de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priued of faithful Paſtors &amp; Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters is a ſigne of Gods wrath and diſpleaſure againſt a people, and to haue them is a ſigne of mercie.</head>
               <pb facs="tcp:15173:37"/>
               <p>SVrely I will no more ſpare thoſe that dwell in the lande,<note place="margin">Zachar. 11<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ℣, 6, 15, 16.</note> ſaith the Lorde, &amp;c. And the Lord ſaid vnto mee, take to thée yet the inſtrumentes of a fooliſh ſhep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heard, for loe, I will raiſe vp a ſhephard in the land, which ſhall not looke for the thing that is loſt, nor ſéeke the tender lambs, nor heale that which is hurt, nor féede that which ſtandeth, but he ſhal eat the fleſh of the fat, and teare their paws in pieces.</p>
               <p>The daies of viſitation are come:<note place="margin">Oſei 9, v. 7.</note> the daies of recompence are come: Iſraell ſhall knowe it: the prophet is a foole, the ſpirituall man is mad for the multitude of thine iniquities: therefore the hatred is great.</p>
               <p>We ſée not our ſigns,<note place="margin">Pſal. 74, 9.</note> there is not one Prophet more, nor any with vs that knoweth how long.</p>
               <p>Behold the daies come ſaith the Lord God,<note place="margin">Amos 8, 11.</note> that I will ſende a famine in the lande, not a famine of bread, and a thirſt for water, but of hearing the word of the Lord.</p>
               <p>For loe,<note place="margin">Eſay 3, v. 1, 2</note> the Lorde God of hoſtes will take away fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Ieruſalem, &amp;c. The iudge &amp; the prophet, the prudent and the aged.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:15173:38"/>
               <p>Beholde,<note place="margin">Eſay 24, ℣ſ. 1, 2.</note> the Lorde maketh the earth emptie, and hée maketh it waſte, hée tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth it vpſide downe, and ſcattereſh a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad the inhabitants thereof, and there ſhall be like people like Prieſt, like ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant like maiſter.</p>
               <p>Turne againe,<note place="margin">Ierem. 3. ℣ſe 34 15.</note> O ye diſobedient chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, (ſaith the Lorde) for I am your Lorde, and I wil take you one of a Citie and two of a tribe, and will bring you to <hi>Zion.</hi> And I will giue you Paſtors ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to mine heart, which ſhall féede you with knowledge &amp; vnderſtanding.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="21" type="part">
               <head>21 That parents ought to inſtruct their children, and bring them vp in the feare of the Lord, &amp; not to prouoke them with bitternes.</head>
               <p>AND when your children aſke you what ſeruice is this you kéepe,<note place="margin">Exod. 12, ℣ſ. 25, 27.</note> then ye ſhal ſay it is the ſacrifice of the Lords paſſeouer, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>And the Lord ſaid,<note place="margin">Gen. 18, ℣ſe 17, 19.</note> ſhal I hide from <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham</hi> that thing which I doe? For I knowe him, that he will commaund his ſonnes and houſhold after him, that they kéepe the way of the Lord, and do righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſnes and iudgement.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:15173:38"/>
               <p>And theſe wordes which I commaund thée this day ſhalbe in thine heart,<note place="margin">Deut. 6, ℣ſe 7.8.</note> &amp; thou ſhalt rehearſe them co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinually vnto thy child, and ſhalt talke of them when thou tarrieſt in thine houſe, &amp; as thou walkeſt by the way, and when thou lyeſt downe, and when thou riſeſt vp.</p>
               <p>Howe hee eſtabliſhed a teſtimonie in <hi>Iacob,</hi> &amp; ordained a law in Iſrael,<note place="margin">Pſal. 78, ℣ſe 5, 6, 7, 8.</note> which he commanded our fathers y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they ſhould teache their children, that the poſteritie might knowe it, and the children which ſhould be borne ſhould ſtand vp &amp; declare it to their children, that they might ſette their hope on God, &amp; not forget y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> works of God, but kéepe his commandements, &amp; not to bee as their Fathers, a diſobedient and rebellious generation.</p>
               <p>Ye fathers,<note place="margin">Epheſ. 6.1.</note> prouoke not your children to wrath, but bring them vp in inſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and information of the Lord.</p>
               <p>Fathers,<note place="margin">Colloſ. 3, 2.</note> prouoke not your children to anger, leaſt they be diſcouraged.</p>
               <p>Teach a child in the trade of his way,<note place="margin">Prou. 22, 6</note> and when he is olde he ſhall not departe from it.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Example.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And hee (that is <hi>Eliſha</hi> the Prophet)<note place="margin">2 Kin. 2, ve. 23, 24.</note>
                  <pb facs="tcp:15173:39"/>went vp from thence vnto Bethel, &amp; as he was going vp the way little children came out of the Citie and mocked him, &amp; ſaid to him: come vp thou bald head, come vp thou bald heade. And he turned backe and looked on them, and curſed them in the name of the Lorde, and two beares came out of the forreſt, and tore in pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces two and fortie children of them. A iuſt iudgement of God both vpon the pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents and children: vpon the parents be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they taught them no better: vppon the children for mocking the holie Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet of God. But it is made but a ſmall fault in our dayes t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> floute Gods holie miniſters, and deride them by theſe and ſuch like tearmes: Lo our Sir Iohn; our pelting prieſt, yea and knaue prieſt. And thus they hate them,<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>os<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 5, 10.</note> as ſaith the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet, that reprooue in the gate, and not children, but thoſe that béeing of ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent yeares ſhould haue more knowledge and feare of God.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="22" type="part">
               <head>22. That parents ought to giue correc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to their children if neede re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire, alſo beſide inſtruction.</head>
               <p>HE that ſpareth his rodde hateth his<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ou. 13, 24</note>
                  <pb facs="tcp:15173:39"/>ſonne, but he that loueth him chaſteneth betime.</p>
               <p>Withhold not correction from y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> child,<note place="margin">Prou. 23.13.</note> if thou ſmite him with the rodde he ſhal not die, thou ſhalt ſmite him with the rod, and deliuer his ſoule from hell.</p>
               <p>Chaſten thy ſon while there is hope,<note place="margin">Prou. 19, 18.</note> and lette not thy ſoule ſpare for his mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muring.</p>
               <p>Fooliſhneſſe is bound in the hart of a childe,<note place="margin">Prou. 22, 15.</note> but the rod of correction ſhal driue it away.</p>
               <p>The rod &amp; correction giue wiſedome,<note place="margin">Prou. 29, 15.</note> but a child ſet at liberty maketh his mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther aſhamed.</p>
               <p>Correct thy ſonne,<note place="margin">Prou. 29, 17</note> and he wil giue thée reſt, and wil giue pleaſures to thy ſoule.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Example of Gods iudgements.</head>
               <p>Then the Lord ſaid to <hi>Samuel,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1, Sam. 3. ver. 11, 12, 13.</note> behold I will doe a thing in Iſraell, whereof whoſoeuer ſhal heare, his two eares ſhal tingle. In that day I will raiſe vp a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Eli all things that I haue ſpoken concerning his houſe, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I begin I wil alſo make an end. And I haue tolde him that I will iudge his houſe for euer, for the iniquitie which he knoweth, becauſe his ſonnes ranne into a ſlaunder, and he
<pb facs="tcp:15173:40"/>ſtaied them not.</p>
               <p>And <hi>Adonias</hi> the ſonne of <hi>Haggith,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. Kin 1, verſ. 5, 6.</note> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alted himſelfe, ſaying: I wil be king, and he got him chariots &amp; horſemen, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>fty men to run before him. And his Father would not diſpleaſe him from his child<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hoode to ſay why haſt thou done ſo, and he was a verie goodly man. Beholde what fruite commeth of cockering children, euen to be driue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by them out of our hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes by Gods iuſt iudgement.</p>
               <p>To let our children when they ſinne in our ſight eſcape vnpuniſhed,<note place="margin">1, Sam. 2, 29</note> is to honor them more then God.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="23" type="part">
               <head>23 That children are to obey their pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rentes in their lawfull commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</head>
               <p>CHildren,<note place="margin">Colloſ. 3, 20</note> obey your parentes in all things: for that is well pleaſing vnto the Lord.</p>
               <p>Children,<note place="margin">Epheſ. 6, 1.</note> obey your parents in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lord for this is right.</p>
               <p>Honor thy father and thy mother.<note place="margin">Exod. 20. Prou. 1, verſe 10, 11.</note>
               </p>
               <p>My ſon, heare thy fathers inſtructio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; forſake not thy mothers teachinges. For they ſhalbe a comely orname<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t vnto thine head, &amp; as chaines for thy necke.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="24" type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>24 What lawe God appointed for the
<pb facs="tcp:15173:40"/>puniſhment of a diſobedient ſonne in Iſrael.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>IF any man haue a ſonne that is ſtub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borne and diſobedient,<note place="margin">Deut. 21, ver 18.19.</note> which will not harken vnto the voice of his father, &amp; the voice of his mother, and they haue cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtened him, &amp; hee would not obey them: then ſhal his father and his mother take him, &amp; bring him out to the elders of his Citie, &amp; vnto the gate of the place where he dwelleth, &amp; ſhal ſay to the elders of his Citie, this our ſon is ſtubborne &amp; diſobe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient, &amp; he will not obey our admonitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, he is a riatour and a drunkard. Then all the men of the Citie ſhal ſtone him with ſtones vnto death: ſo thou ſhalt take a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way euil from among you, that all Iſra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ell may heare it and feare.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="25" type="part">
               <head>25 That all ſeruantes are to obey their maiſters, and to ſerue them fayth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully, and to beare paciently their rebukes without murmuring, and alſo to honour them.</head>
               <p>LEt as many ſeruants as are vnder y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> yoke count their maiſters woorthy of all honour,<note place="margin">1, Tim. 6, ℣. 1.2.</note> that the name of God and his doctrine bee not euill ſpoken of, and
<pb facs="tcp:15173:41"/>they which haue beléeuing maiſters, let them not deſpiſe them becauſe they are brethren, but rather doe ſeruice becauſe they are faithfull, and beloued, and par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takers of the benefite.</p>
               <p>Let ſeruantes be ſubiect to their may<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters,<note place="margin">Titus 2, verſ. 9, 10.</note> and pleaſe them in all thinges, not anſwering againe, neither pickers, but that they ſhew all good faithfulnes, that they may adorne the doctrine of God our ſauiour in all things.</p>
               <p>Seruants,<note place="margin">Epheſ. 6, ver. 5, 6, 7.</note> be obedient vnto them that are your maiſters according to the fleſh, with feare &amp; trembling in ſingleneſſe of your harts, as vnto Chriſt: not w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſeruice to the eye as men pleaſers, but as the ſeruants of Chriſt, doing the wil of God from the hart with goodwill, ſeruing the Lord and not men: and knowe yee that whatſoeuer good thing any man doth, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame hée ſhall receiue of the Lord, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he be bond or frée.</p>
               <p>Seruants,<note place="margin">Colloſ. 3. ℣ſe 22, 23, 24, 25.</note> be obedient vnto them that are your maiſters according to the fleſh, in all thinges: not with eye ſeruice as men pleaſers, but in ſinglenes of heart fearing God, and whatſoeuer ye doe, doe it hartily, as to the Lorde and not vnto
<pb facs="tcp:15173:41"/>men knowing that of the Lorde yée ſhall receiue the rewarde of the inheritance, for ye ſerue the Lord Chriſt, but hée that doth wrong, ſhall receiue for the wrong that he hath done, and there is no reſpect of perſons.</p>
               <p>Seruants,<note place="margin">1, Pet. 2. ℣ſe 18, 19, 20. 21.</note> be ſubiect to your maiſters with all feare, not only to the good &amp; cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous, but alſo to the froward. For this is thank worthy, if a man for conſcience toward God endure griefe, ſuffering wrongfully. For what praiſe is it if whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ye be buffeted for your faults, ye take it patiently; but and if when ye do wel, ye ſuffer wrong and take it patiently, this is acceptable to God. For hereunto yee are called, for Chriſt alſo ſuffered for vs, leauing for vs an example that ye ſhould follow his ſteppes.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Iacob an example of a faithfull ſeruant to Laban.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This twentie yeare haue I béen with thée,<note place="margin">Gen. 21, verſe 38, 39, 40.</note> thine ewes and thy goates haue not caſt their young, and the Rammes of thy flocke haue I not eaten. Whatſoeuer was torne of beaſts I brought it not vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thée, but made it good my ſelfe: of mine hande diddeſt thou require it, were yt
<pb facs="tcp:15173:42"/>ſtollen by day, or ſtollen by night, I was in the day conſumed with heat, and froſt in the night, and my ſléepe departed from mine eies.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="26" type="part">
               <head>26 That Maiſters and Miſtreſſes owe duties to their ſeruantes, and what thoſe duties are.</head>
               <p>ANd ye Maiſters,<note place="margin">Epheſ. 6, 9.</note> doe the ſame thing vnto them (that is your ſeruants) put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting away threatning, &amp; know that euen your maiſter alſo is in heauen, neither is there reſpect of perſon with God.</p>
               <p>Ye maiſters,<note place="margin">Colloſ. 4, 1.</note> do you vnto your ſerua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts that which is iuſt and equall, knowing that ye alſo haue a maiſter in heauen.</p>
               <p>A ſeruant will not bee chaſtened with words,<note place="margin">Prou. 29, 19</note> though he vnderſtand, yet wil he not anſwere. Such a ſeruant then when he is knowne muſt haue the ſcourge.</p>
               <p>He that delicately bringeth vp his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant from his youth,<note place="margin">Prou. 29, 21</note> at length he wil bée euen as his ſonne: which is by maiſters to be conſidered of.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Example of Iobs good dealing with his ſeruants farre from rigour.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:15173:42"/>
               <p>IF I did condemn the iudgement of my ſeruant,<note place="margin">Iob 31, verſe 13, 14, 15.</note> and of my mayde whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they did contend with mee, what then ſhall I doe when God ſtandeth vp, and when he ſhal viſite me, what ſhall I anſwere? hée that hath made me in the wombe, hath he not made him? hath not hee alone faſhioned vs in the wombe? Hereby may thoſe ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters ſée their wickednes, which wil not heare their ſeruants ſpeake, but vppon a ſimple ſurmiſe and brainſicknes, do euil intreat them by cruell ſtripes, when in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>déede there is no iuſt cauſe.</p>
               <p>Thou ſhalt not oppreſſe an hyred ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant,<note place="margin">Deut. 24, 14</note> that is néedie &amp; poore, neither of thy brethren, nor ſtraunger, thou ſhalt giue him his hyre for his day.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="27" type="part">
               <head>27 What the duties of huſbands are vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to their wiues.</head>
               <p>LIkewiſe yee huſbandes,<note place="margin">1, Pet 3, 7.</note> dwell with them (that are your wiues) as men of knowledge, giuing honour vnto the woman, as vnto the weaker veſſell, euen as they which are heires together of the grace of life, that your praiers be not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terrupted.</p>
               <p>Let the huſband giue vnto the wife due<note place="margin">1, Cor. 7, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note>
                  <pb facs="tcp:15173:43"/>beneuolence, and likewiſe alſo the wife vnto the huſband.</p>
               <p>Huſbands,<note place="margin">Colloſ. 3, 19</note> loue your wiues, and be not bitter vnto them.</p>
               <p>Huſbandes,<note place="margin">Epheſ. 5. ℣ſe 25, 26, 28.</note> loue your wiues euen as Chriſt loued the Church, and gaue him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe for it, that hee might ſanctifie it, &amp;c. ſo ought men to loue their wiues, as their owne bodies. Hee that loueth his wife, loueth himſelfe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="28" type="part">
               <head>28 What the duties of wiues bee vnto their huſbands.</head>
               <p>WIues,<note place="margin">Epheſ. 5.22.</note> ſubmit your ſelues vnto your huſbands, as vnto the Lord: for the huſband is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wiues head, euen as Chriſt is the head of the Church, &amp; the ſame is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſauiour of his body: therefore as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> church is in ſubiection to Chriſt, euen ſo let the wiues be to their huſba<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds in all things.</p>
               <p>The man is the womans head.<note place="margin">1, Cor. 11, 3. 1, Cor. 7, 3.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Let the wife giue vnto her huſband due beneuolence.</p>
               <p>Wiues,<note place="margin">Colloſ. 3, 18.</note> ſubmit your ſelues vnto your huſbands, as it is comely in the Lord.</p>
               <p>Likewiſe alſo the women,<note place="margin">1. Tim. 2, 9.10, 11, 12, 13</note> that they array themſelues in comely apparell, with ſhamefaſtnes and modeſtie, not
<pb facs="tcp:15173:43"/>with broidered haire, or gold, or pearles, or coſtly apparel, but as becommeth wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men that profeſſe the feare of God with good workes. Let the women learne in ſilence with all ſubiection, I permit not a woman to teach, neither to vſurpe au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie ouer the man, but to be in ſile<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce: for <hi>Adam</hi> was firſt formed, then <hi>Eue,</hi> &amp; <hi>Adam</hi> was not deceiued, but the woman was deceiued, and was in the tranſgreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion: notwithſtanding through bearing of children ſhe ſhall be ſaued, if they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue in faith and loue, and holines with modeſtie.</p>
               <p>Let the wife ſée that ſhe feare her huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band.<note place="margin">Epheſ. 5, 33.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Vnto the woman hee ſaide (that is the Lord) I wil greatly increaſe thy ſorow,<note place="margin">Gen. 3, 16.</note> &amp; thy conceptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, in ſorow ſhalt thou bring forth children, &amp; thy deſire ſhalbe ſubiect to thy huſband, &amp; he ſhal rule ouer thée.</p>
               <p>Let your women kéepe ſilence in the Churches,<note place="margin">1, Cor. 14, ℣ 34, 35.</note> for it is not permitted vnto them to ſpeake: but they ought to be ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect as alſo the lawe ſaith, &amp; if they will learn any thing, let them aſke their huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bands at home, for it is a ſhame for wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men to ſpeake in the Church.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:15173:44"/>
               <p>Likewiſe let the wiues bee ſubiect to their huſbandes,<note place="margin">1, Pet. 3, verſe 1, 2, 3, 4.5, 16.</note> that euen they which o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey not the word, may without the word be woon by the conuerſatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the wiues. While they behelde your pure conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation, which is with feare: whoſe appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>relling let it not be outwarde, as with broidered haire, and golde put about, or in putting on of apparell. But let the hid man of the heart bee vncorrupt with a méeke and quiet ſpirite, which is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God a thing much ſette by. For e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen after this manner in times paſt, did the holie women which truſted in God, attire themſelues, and were ſubiecte to their huſbandes. As <hi>Sara</hi> obeyed <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham,</hi> and called him Sir, whoſe daughters yee are whileſt yée doe well, not béeing afrayd of any terrour.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Dutie of huſband and wife.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The wife hath not the power of her owne bodie,<note place="margin">1, Cor. 7, 4.5</note> but the huſband: and lyke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe alſo the huſband hath not power of his owne bodie, but the wife. Defraude not one another, (that is, leaue not one anothers bed) except it be with conſente for a time, that ye may giue your ſelues to faſting and praier, and againe come
<pb facs="tcp:15173:44"/>together, that Sathan tempt you not for your incontinencie.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="29" type="part">
               <head>29 That one Chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ought to inſtruct edifie, and exhort another.</head>
               <p>WHerefore exhorte one another,<note place="margin">ſ, Theſ, 5, 11</note> and edifie one another euen as ye do.</p>
               <p>Take héede brethren,<note place="margin">Heb. 3, ver. 13, 14.</note> leaſt at any time there bée in any of you an euill hart, and vnfaithfull to departe away from the ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing God: but exhort one another daily while it is called to day, leaſt any of you bée hardned through the deceitfulneſſe of ſinne.</p>
               <p>And let vs conſider one another to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoke vnto loue,<note place="margin">Heb. 10, 2.</note> &amp; to good woorkes, not for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaking the fellowſhip that wee haue a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong our ſelues, as the manner of ſome is, but let vs exhort one another, &amp; that ſo much the more, bicauſe you ſée that the day draweth néere.</p>
               <p>Then ſpake they that feared the Lord,<note place="margin">Mal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> .3, 16</note> euerie one to his neighbour, &amp; the Lorde harkened and heard it, and a booke of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance was written before him for them that feared the Lord.</p>
               <p>The righteous teacheth the houſe of the wicked.<note place="margin">Prou. 21, 1</note>
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:15173:45"/>
               <p>The lippes of the righteous féede ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie.<note place="margin">Prou. 10, 21</note>
               </p>
               <p>Let euerie man as hee hath receiued y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> gift,<note place="margin">1, Pet, 4, 10.</note> miniſter the ſame one to another, as good diſpoſers of the manifolde grace of God.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="30" type="part">
               <head>30 That euerie Chriſtian is bounde in conſcience, when his brother ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth, to rebuke him for his ſinne.</head>
               <p>THou ſhalt not hate thy brother in thy heart,<note place="margin">Leuit. 19, 17</note> but thou ſhalt plainly rebuke thy neighbour, and ſuffer him not to ſinne.</p>
               <p>Let the righteous ſmite me,<note place="margin">Pſal. 141, 5.</note> for that it is a benefite, and let him reprooue me, &amp; it ſhall bee a pretious oyle that ſhall not break my head, for within a while I ſhal euen pray in their miſeries.</p>
               <p>We deſire you brethren, admoniſh the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that are vnruly,<note place="margin">1, Theſ, 5, 14</note> comfort the féeble min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, beare with the weake, be patient to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards all men.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="31" type="part">
               <head>31 That priuate offences are to bee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buked priuately or ſecretly.</head>
               <p>IF thy brother treſpaſſe againſt thée,<note place="margin">Math. 18, 15</note> go and tell him his fault betwéene thée
<pb facs="tcp:15173:45"/>and him alone, if he heare thée, thou haſt wonne thy brother.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="32" type="part">
               <head>32. That open ſinne muſt haue open rebuke.</head>
               <p>THem that ſinne rebuke openly,<note place="margin">1. Tim. 5.20</note> that the reſt alſo may feare.</p>
               <p>And whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                  <hi>Peter</hi> was come to <hi>Antioch</hi> I withſtood him openly,<note place="margin">Galat. 2, 11.</note> for he was wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie to be rebuked.</p>
               <p>He that rebuketh a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhall find more fauour at the length,<note place="margin">Prou. 28, 23.</note> then he that flatte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth him with his lips, why then ſhould any man caſt any of theſe doubts? why then I ſhall looſe his good will, and I am afraid he will not take it well, hauing his promiſe of God.</p>
               <p>A reproofe entreth more into him that hath vnderſtanding,<note place="margin">Prou. 17.</note> then an hundreth ſtripes into a foole.</p>
               <p>A ſcorner loueth not him that rebu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth him,<note place="margin">Prou. 15, 12.</note> neither will he go vnto the wiſe.</p>
               <p>A wiſe ſonne will obey the inſtruction of his father,<note place="margin">Prou. 13, 1.</note> but a ſcorner will heare no rebuke.</p>
               <p>Better is it to heare the rebuke of wiſe men,<note place="margin">Prou. 7, 7.</note> then the ſong of fooles.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:15173:46"/>
               <p>He that hardneth his necke when he is rebuked,<note place="margin">Prou. 29, 1.</note> ſhall ſuddenly be deſtroyed and cannot be cured.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="33" type="part">
               <head>33. That no Chriſtian ought to haue a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny felowſhip with any wicked ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, who profeſsing chriſtianitie, lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth his life lewdly to the ſlander of the profeſsion, but to auoid ſuch a one as filthines and dirt.</head>
               <p>IF any that is called a brother (that us to ſay a Chriſtian man) be a fornica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tour,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 5.</note> or couetous, or an idolater, or a rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler, or a drunkard, or an extortioner, with ſuch one eat not.</p>
               <p>Haue no fellowſhip with the vnfruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full workes of darkeneſſe,<note place="margin">Epheſ. 5.11.</note> but euen re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prooue them rather.</p>
               <p>If any man obeye not our ſayings,<note place="margin">1. Theſ. 3. verſe 14.</note> note him by letter, and haue no compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie with him that he may be aſhamed.</p>
               <p>He that walketh with the wiſe ſhal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>be wiſe,<note place="margin">Prou. 13, 20.</note> but a companion of fooles ſhalbe afflicted.</p>
               <p>For,<note place="margin">Epeſ. 5. verſe 6.7.</note> for ſuch things co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth the wrath of God vpon the children of diſobedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, be not therefore companions with them.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:15173:46"/>
               <p>They that forſake the law praiſe the wicked,<note place="margin">Prou. 28, 4.</note> but they that kéepe the law ſet themſelues againſt them.</p>
               <p>Lord who ſhall dwell in thy taberna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle,<note place="margin">Pſal. 15.1, 4.</note> &amp;c. He in whoſe eies a vile perſon is contemned: but he honoureth them that feare the Lord.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Example.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">℣ſe </seg>2</label> And <hi>Iehu</hi> the ſon of <hi>Hannani</hi> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Seer went to méet him (that is <hi>Iehoſhaphat</hi> who went to the war with <hi>Ahab</hi> king of Iſraell) and ſaid to king <hi>Iehoſhaphat,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2. Chron. 19.</note> wouldeſt thou helpe the wicked, and loue them that hate the Lord? therefore for this thing the wrath of the Lord is vpon thée.</p>
               <p>Yet after this did <hi>Iehoſhaphat</hi> king of <hi>Iudah</hi> ioyne himſelfe with <hi>Ahaziah</hi> king of Iſraell who was giuen to do e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill,<note place="margin">2. Chron. 20 ℣ſ. 35, 36, 37</note> and he ioyned with him to make ſhips to go to <hi>Tarſhiſh,</hi> &amp; they made the ſhips in <hi>Ezion Gaber,</hi> then <hi>Eliezer</hi> the ſon of <hi>Dodauah</hi> of <hi>Mereſha</hi> propheſied againſt <hi>Iehoſhaphat,</hi> ſaying: becauſe thou haſt ioyned thy ſelfe with <hi>Ahaziah</hi> the Lord hath broken thy workes, &amp; the ſhips were broken that they were not able to go to <hi>Tarſhiſh.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="34" type="part">
               <head>
                  <pb facs="tcp:15173:47"/>34. <hi>That all Chriſtians ought to be full of good workes, and to what end.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>FOr wée are his workemanſhip crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in Chriſt Ieſus vnto good works,<note place="margin">Epheſ. 2, 10.</note> which God hath ordeined, that we ſhould walke in them.</p>
               <p>This is a true ſaying,<note place="margin">Titus 3, 8.</note> &amp; theſe things I will thou ſhouldeſt affirme, that they which haue beléeued God might be care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to ſhew forth good works, theſe are good and profitable to men.</p>
               <p>Who gaue himſelfe for vs,<note place="margin">Titus 2, 14.</note> to redéeme vs from all iniquitie, and to purge vs a peculiar people vnto himſelfe, zealous of good workes.</p>
               <p>Charge them that are rich in this world that they be not high minded,<note place="margin">1. Tim. 6, 17</note> &amp; that they truſt not in vncertaine riches but in the liuing God, which giueth vs aboundantly all things to enioy, that they do good and be rich in good workes, and ready to diſtribute and communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>End of good workes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Let your light ſo ſhine before men,<note place="margin">Math. 5.16.</note> that they may ſée your good workes, and
<pb facs="tcp:15173:47"/>glorifie your father which is in heauen.</p>
               <p>And haue your conuerſation honeſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Gentils,<note place="margin">1. Pet. 2, 12.</note> that they which ſpeake euill of you as of euill doers, may by your good works which they ſhal ſée, glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rifie God in the day of their viſitation.</p>
               <p>And this I pray that your loue may abound,<note place="margin">Philip. 1. ℣ſe 9, 10, 11.</note> yet more and more in know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge and in all iudgement, that ye may diſcerne things that differ one from an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other, that ye may be pure and without offence vntill the day of Chriſt, filled with the fruits of righteouſneſſe, which are by Ieſus Chriſt vnto the glorie and praiſe of God.</p>
               <p>Ioine moreouer vertue with your faith,<note place="margin">2, Pet. 1. ℣ſe 5, 6, 7.</note> and with vertue knowledge, and with knowledge temperance, and with temperance patience, and with pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence godlineſſe, and with godlineſſe bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therly kindneſſe, and with brotherly kindneſſe loue. For if theſe things vs among you and abound, they will make you that ye neither ſhalbe idle, nor vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fruitfull in the knowledge of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt, for he that hath not theſs things, is blind, and cannot ſée farre of, and hath forgotten that he was purged
<pb facs="tcp:15173:48"/>from his old ſinnes.</p>
               <p>And let ours learne to ſhewe foorth good works for neceſſarie vſes,<note place="margin">Titus 3.14.</note> that they be not vnfruitfull.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Now good Reader this being ended, there remaineth nothing but thy di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lige<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, carefully to practiſe that which thou ſhalt here find, as thy calling ſhal require, and bind thee, which that thou maiſt do, I ſhal not ceaſe to pray. And thus in Chriſt I bid thee farewell.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:15173:48"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
